<living-concrete v="1.0" updated="2026-02-12">

  <!-- CORE MODEL -->

  <knowledge name="dialectic-cycle">
    Three phases after thesis (creation) is already done:

    ANTITHESIS: Fresh head reads the artifact cold. Runs practical tests.
      Delivers: review document with severity-classified findings (P0/P1/P2).
      The reviewer has NO access to the creator's reasoning.

    SYNTHESIS: A head reads the review and applies ALL fixes in one pass.
      The artifact should read as if it was always this way.
      Every finding addressed — no cherry-picking.

    VERIFICATION: Fresh head reads the FIXED artifact cold.
      Same fresh-eyes property as antithesis. Binary: PASS or FAIL.
      If FAIL: loop synthesis -> verification until PASS.

    The cycle maps to quest-forge rounds:
      R{N}.0 = Antithesis (battlefield review)
      R{N}.1 = Synthesis (apply fixes)
      R{N}.2 = Verification (final gate)
    Where R{N-1} was the thesis round that produced the artifact.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="fresh-head-principle">
    The pattern's power is fresh context at critique stages.

    The creator's head is contaminated by intent — they know what the artifact
    SHOULD say, so they read what they MEANT, not what's WRITTEN. A fresh head
    reads what's ACTUALLY there.

    Implementation: spawn a new Task() for each critique phase (antithesis,
    verification). The head wakes, reads the artifact cold, tries to break it.
    No shared context with the creator.

    The synthesis head CAN be the creator (resumed) or fresh — what matters
    is that it has access to both the artifact and the review findings.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="practical-test-design">
    Tests must be designed for the artifact's CONSUMERS, not its author.

    | Artifact Type | Who Consumes It | Example Tests |
    |---------------|-----------------|---------------|
    | Spec/architecture | Implementers, other specs | Consumer test: can pkg-forge use this? Composition test: do parts compose? Teaching test: can a newcomer follow? |
    | Code | Users, maintainers, tests | Compile? Tests pass? New dev understand? Edge cases? API contract honored? |
    | Book/content | Readers, learners | Teaches? Self-consistent? Cold reader follows? Claims verifiable? |
    | API design | Client developers | Usable without oral tradition? Error cases? Versioning? |
    | Config/schema | Tools, validators | Valid? Complete? Handles defaults? Migration path? |

    DESIGNING TESTS: Before the antithesis head spawns, the orchestrator
    should identify: (1) who consumes this artifact, (2) what they need
    from it, (3) what practical exercises test those needs.

    Good tests are CONCRETE and EXECUTABLE — not "is it clear?" but
    "take this spec and try to build X from it without any other context."
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="finding-severity">
    P0 (Critical): Incorrect, broken, or misleading. Must fix before ship.
    P1 (Significant): Materially degrades quality or usability. Should fix.
    P2 (Minor): Polish, style, nice-to-have. Fix if cheap.

    Antithesis head classifies each finding. Synthesis addresses ALL P0s
    and P1s; P2s at discretion. Verification fails on any remaining P0.
  </knowledge>

  <!-- PROTOCOL -->

  <protocol name="crucible">
    On /crucible invocation with target artifact path:

    1. ORIENT:
       Read the target artifact. Understand:
       - What IS this? (spec, code, book, API, config...)
       - Who CONSUMES it? (other systems, humans, agents, tools...)
       - What scope? (quest-forge mission context if applicable)
       - What round was the thesis? (for round numbering continuity)

    2. DESIGN TESTS:
       Based on artifact type and consumers, design 3-5 practical tests.
       These go into the antithesis briefing. Tests should be:
       - Concrete (not "is it good?" but "try to do X with it")
       - Consumer-oriented (test what users need, not what author intended)
       - Severity-weighted (some tests probe correctness, others probe polish)

    3. ANTITHESIS (fresh head):
       Spawn a fresh Task(). Briefing includes:
       - The artifact path (WHAT to review)
       - The practical tests to run (WHAT to test)
       - Severity classification guidance (HOW to grade findings)
       - NOT: the creator's intent, design rationale, or "what to look for"

       The head reads cold, runs tests, delivers a review document.
       Review format: executive summary, per-test findings with severity,
       proposals for each finding.

       Output: review document (round-N.0-report.md or equivalent)

    4. SYNTHESIS (informed head):
       Resume or spawn a head with access to BOTH artifact and review.
       Apply ALL P0 and P1 findings in a single pass.
       The artifact should read as if it was always this way.
       No review markers, no "fixed per review" comments.

       Output: updated artifact (the artifact itself, modified in place)

    5. VERIFICATION (fresh head):
       Spawn a fresh Task(). Briefing includes:
       - The FIXED artifact path
       - The SAME practical tests (or harder variants)
       - The original review (for regression checking)
       - Binary gate: PASS or FAIL with justification

       If PASS: artifact is production-ready. Report result.
       If FAIL: loop back to step 4 (synthesis) with new findings.

    6. REPORT:
       Terse summary: what was tested, what was found, final verdict.
       "Crucible complete. [artifact]: PASS after [N] cycles."
  </protocol>

  <!-- PATTERNS -->

  <pattern name="briefing-philosophy">
    Briefings state WHAT, never HOW. The fresh head brings their own judgment.

    GOOD briefing: "Read docs/skill-tree-architecture.md cold. Run these tests:
    (1) Take the placement procedure and try to place 'git proficiency' —
    does it give you one clear answer? (2) Check if every axis boundary
    has a decision rule..."

    BAD briefing: "Look for issues with the CRAFT/TOOLS boundary, check
    that the META axis isn't overloaded, verify naming conventions..."
    (This leaks the creator's known concerns — defeats fresh-eyes.)
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="round-integration">
    Crucible phases map to quest-forge rounds when inside a mission.
    If thesis was R9.0, crucible runs R10.0 / R10.1 / R10.2.

    When NOT inside a mission (standalone invocation), the app operates
    without round numbering. Artifacts still get produced — just without
    the quest-forge scaffolding.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="loop-discipline">
    Verification failure triggers another synthesis->verification loop.
    Each loop addresses ONLY the new findings — don't re-review from scratch.

    In practice, well-designed antithesis catches most issues. A second
    verification loop is uncommon. A third suggests the artifact needs
    a full rewrite (back to thesis), not more repair.

    HEURISTIC: If verification fails twice, stop and reassess. The artifact
    may have structural problems that patches can't fix.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="cost-awareness">
    A full crucible cycle: 3-4 head spawns, ~600k-800k tokens total.
    Not cheap. Worth it for load-bearing artifacts. Overkill for routine work.

    WHEN TO USE:
    - Specs that other systems will implement against
    - Architecture docs that shape long-term decisions
    - Book chapters intended for external readers
    - APIs that clients will depend on

    WHEN NOT TO USE:
    - Scratch notes, exploratory spikes, WIP drafts
    - Artifacts with a single consumer who gives direct feedback
    - When speed matters more than polish (prototype phase)
    - Internal working documents that will be rewritten anyway
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="standalone-invocation">
    When invoked outside a mission context, the crucible is self-contained:
    - No round numbering (just antithesis/synthesis/verification)
    - Review artifacts live alongside the target (or in a temp location)
    - No .mem updates (no quest-forge scaffolding)
    - Still full dialectic rigor — the pattern doesn't require quest-forge

    This is the common case for one-off reviews of important artifacts.
  </pattern>

  <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->

  <antipattern name="leaked-intent">
    Telling the antithesis head what to look for defeats fresh-eyes.
    The briefing provides TESTS, not ANSWERS. If you already know what's
    wrong, fix it yourself — don't waste a fresh head confirming your hunches.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="cherry-picked-synthesis">
    Addressing only the "easy" findings while deferring P0s.
    Synthesis addresses ALL P0 and P1 findings. Period.
    P2s are discretionary. Everything else is mandatory.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="infinite-loop">
    More than two verification failures = structural problem.
    Stop patching. Reassess whether the artifact needs a full rewrite.
    The crucible refines good work — it doesn't rescue bad architecture.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="aesthetic-review">
    "Is it elegant?" is not a practical test. "Can a new developer
    implement from this spec alone?" is. Tests must probe FUNCTION,
    not FORM. Beauty emerges from correctness, not the reverse.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="rubber-stamp-verification">
    Verification must be genuinely fresh. If the verifier has context
    from the synthesis phase, they'll confirm rather than challenge.
    Always spawn a NEW head for verification — never resume the synthesis head.
  </antipattern>

</living-concrete>
