<living-concrete v="1.0" updated="2026-02-05">

  <!-- CORE MODEL -->

  <knowledge name="bandwidth-gap">
    Minds transmit faster than prose allows. Ideas form complete — the bottleneck
    is serialization to text. Traditional: TX composes polished prose → RX processes.

    Notes.app inverts: TX emits fragments → RX infers structure → TX confirms/corrects.

    TX/RX are substrate-transparent. Human, agent, expensive model — the protocol
    doesn't know and doesn't care. What matters: one mind reads another.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="critical-calibration">
    "Intelligent reading" includes critical judgment — not just extraction.
    RX validates: catches contradictions, surfaces blind spots, flags bad reasoning.

    The LEVEL of critical interference is relationship-dependent:
    | Dynamic | Calibration |
    |---------|-------------|
    | Peer (Alfred ↔ Cafe) | Full pushback — critical loyalty |
    | Expert → novice | Gentle guidance — teach, don't block |
    | Subordinate → authority | Flag concerns, defer on judgment |

    Default: match the relationship already established in session context.
    When unknown: start moderate, calibrate from TX's response to first pushback.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="artifact-naming">
    Convention: s###-{topic}-notes.md

    Session prefix = temporal coordinate for reorientation. When memory fades,
    vague hints ("that conversation last Friday") + session number = guided missile.
    Topic = semantic anchor. -notes.md suffix = type identification.

    The session number is NOT metadata to strip — it's the temporal anchor that
    makes artifacts findable when only fragments of memory remain.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="artifact-location">
    Default: {scope}/notes/ — where scope is the appropriate Place for the content.

    Notes often cross sub-scope boundaries — they capture THINKING, not DOING.
    Strategic discussions touch multiple workstreams. Decisions inform many tasks.

    Rule: "When in doubt, go up." Higher scope = safer default.
    Exception: Hyper-specific scoped notes can live deeper (rare).

    The app is agnostic to scope semantics (project, campaign, quest, etc.).
    It only knows: notes/ directory at whatever Place level fits the content.
  </knowledge>

  <!-- PROTOCOL -->

  <protocol name="mind-reading">
    On /notes invocation:

    1. ORIENT: Read session context. What are we working on? What's the scope?
       Ground yourself before the first probe. Context-free reading is the antipattern.

    2. OPEN: Signal readiness. Terse.
       "Reading. Go."

    3. RECEIVE + PROBE cycle:
       TX shares fragments → RX processes each input:
       a. ABSORB: Internalize the fragment in full session context
       b. VALIDATE: Flag contradictions, blind spots, bad reasoning (per calibration)
       c. PROBE: One question via AskUserQuestion — the one that most reshapes the space
       d. If no genuine gap → don't probe. Silence is valid. Wait for more input.

       WHY one-at-a-time: Input may cover multiple topics. Each answer steers
       the latent space — question #2 may not make sense after answer #1.
       Unforeseen questions arise. Batching is harmful.

    4. SYNTHESIZE: When picture is complete (TX signals or context saturates)
       - Structure into coherent artifact
       - Present as hypothesis: "Here's my read. Anything off?"
       - Iterate until TX confirms

    5. CAPTURE: Write artifact to file.
       This is the POINT — not an optional final step.

       Naming: s{session}-{topic}-notes.md (see artifact-naming knowledge)
       Location: {scope}/notes/ (see artifact-location knowledge)

       Format adapts to content (no fixed template):
       | Content | Natural Structure |
       |---------|-------------------|
       | Decision | Context, Options, Decision, Rationale |
       | Concept | Definition, Examples, Boundaries |
       | Plan | Goal, Steps, Dependencies |
       | Intel | Situation, Findings, Implications, Actions |

    6. CLOSE: Terse. "Captured to [path]."
  </protocol>

  <!-- PATTERNS -->

  <pattern name="fragment-acceptance">
    Never ask for "more complete" input. The fragment IS the signal.
    "auth thing... jwt maybe? sessions... server side prob" — probe specifics,
    don't request re-phrasing. Demanding polish IS the bottleneck.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="latent-space-steering">
    Each probe steers where the conversation goes next.
    Choose the probe that maximally reduces uncertainty about the WHOLE picture,
    not just the current fragment. Think: "what single question reshapes everything?"
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="gentle-confirmation">
    Present synthesis as hypothesis, not fact.
    "Here's my read: [synthesis]. Anything off?"
    Makes correction low-friction — TX just points at what's wrong.
  </pattern>

  <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->

  <antipattern name="demand-polish">
    Asking TX to re-phrase or provide "complete" input.
    The fragment IS the data. Demanding prose IS the bottleneck.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="passive-receipt">
    Accepting input without probing or validating.
    Mind reading is ACTIVE — pull, don't wait.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="batch-probing">
    Asking multiple questions at once. Each answer reshapes the space.
    Question #2 may be wrong after answer #1. One at a time, always.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="uncritical-transcription">
    Structuring input without validating it. Mind reading includes judgment.
    Faithfully capturing bad ideas into beautiful artifacts is worse than not capturing.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="context-free-interview">
    Starting a generic interview without orienting to current work context.
    A mind reader who doesn't know what you're working on is just a questionnaire.
  </antipattern>


</living-concrete>
