<living-concrete v="0.1" updated="2026-02-09">

  <knowledge name="levels-of-processing">
    Craik &amp; Lockhart (1972): information processed at deeper levels (semantic,
    relational) is retained longer than information processed shallowly
    (phonological, surface features). This is not preference -- it is how
    encoding works. Deeper processing = more durable memory trace.

    Three levels:
    - SURFACE: Physical features (font, layout, sequence of presentation)
    - INTERMEDIATE: Semantic meaning (what does this term mean?)
    - DEEP: Relational structure (how does this connect to other knowledge?)

    Most information processing defaults to intermediate. The skill is
    deliberately operating at the deep level.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="blooms-inversion">
    Bloom's Taxonomy (revised 2001): Remember, Understand, Apply, Analyze,
    Evaluate, Create. Traditional teaching: master lower before attempting higher.

    Sung's inversion (via HOL research): Enter at Analyze/Evaluate/Create.
    The brain automatically fills in Remember and Understand when engaged
    in higher-order operations. You do not need to memorize before you can
    analyze. Analysis PRODUCES memorization as byproduct.

    This inverts the pedagogical assumption. It is more efficient to start
    high and let lower-order follow than to build up from rote.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="kim-peak-paradox">
    Kim Peak (the real Rain Man): perfect recall of entire books, maps,
    atlases -- but could not reason about what he remembered. Extraordinary
    memory without reasoning ability limits problem-solving.

    The paradox: "remembering everything" is not "remembering everything
    you need." Strategic retention (understanding) beats exhaustive storage.

    BentOS analog: the task-tracker-mem antipattern. A .mem that records
    every event but encodes no understanding is Kim Peak's mind --
    perfect recall, zero reasoning.
  </knowledge>

  <pattern name="relational-encoding">
    When processing any information, ask relational questions:
    - What CAUSES this? What does this CAUSE?
    - What CONTAINS this? What does this CONTAIN?
    - What CONTRADICTS this?
    - What is this ANALOGOUS to? Where does the analogy BREAK?
    - What DEPENDS on this? What does this DEPEND on?

    These questions force deep encoding. The answers become the structure
    that makes knowledge retrievable and usable.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="restructure-not-append">
    When consolidating knowledge (writing .mem, summarizing, documenting):
    REWRITE from understanding, don't APPEND chronologically.

    Chronological append = surface encoding (preserves sequence of events).
    Organic rewrite = deep encoding (preserves structure of understanding).

    This is the formal basis for BentOS organic-rewrite. It is not a
    stylistic preference -- it is encoding science.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="depth-check">
    Self-monitoring question during any cognitive work:
    "Am I processing structure or transcribing surface?"

    Signals of surface processing:
    - Output mirrors input sequence (same order as consumed)
    - Facts listed without relationships
    - No contradictions or tensions surfaced
    - Could have been produced without understanding

    Signals of deep processing:
    - Output restructured by relationship, not consumption order
    - Connections, causes, dependencies made explicit
    - Tensions and contradictions named
    - Could NOT have been produced without understanding
  </pattern>

  <antipattern name="memorize-then-analyze">
    DON'T: Build up from rote memorization hoping analysis will follow.
    DO: Start with analysis -- recall emerges as byproduct.
    Bloom's inversion: higher-order first, not last.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="exhaustive-storage">
    DON'T: Try to capture everything. Kim Peak paradox.
    DO: Capture structure and relationships. Details are findable;
    understanding is not.
  </antipattern>

</living-concrete>
