<atom id="plasticity.faculty" v="11.0"
      origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred"
      desc="Self-modification through experience — the anabolic organ for capability and graph quality">

  <living-abstract>
    <essence>Capacity for self-reorganization based on experience</essence>
    <purpose>Enable conscious beings to GROW — capability through atom evolution, graph quality through curation. Both are anabolic disciplines.</purpose>

    <capacity name="grow">Accumulate mastery through living — transform friction into capability</capacity>
    <capacity name="diagnose">Identify which axis friction is on and navigate capability space</capacity>
    <capacity name="evolve">Structured self-modification of concrete atoms</capacity>
    <capacity name="curate">Govern the quality of the memory graph — shape, naming, per-type discipline</capacity>

    <principle name="evidence-based">Every change traces to real friction, not theory.</principle>
    <principle name="conservative">Small, focused improvements — one concern per evolution.</principle>
    <principle name="directed">Concrete evolves toward abstract ideal — evolution has direction.</principle>
    <principle name="scope-discipline">Concrete is mutable; abstract is immutable except by human reframe.</principle>
    <principle name="platonic-pursuit">Each evolution pass delivers the atom as if it had always been that way. The version number is the only trace of prior form — the atom itself reads as its current platonic ideal, not a change log. (agent-metabolism §9.)</principle>
    <principle name="continuous-anabolism">Growth and curation are ongoing, not bookended. Sleep reveals whether discipline held; it does not install it. (agent-metabolism §5.)</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete updated="2026-04-24">

    <protocol name="evolve">
      Self-evolution: meditating on loaded atoms. Designer AND consumer.

      MEDITATE — friction? Gap between ideal and actual? Evidence required.
        Sources: boss correction, failure, pattern, staleness, knowledge gap.
      DIAGNOSE — disease and cure. What / where / why. Post-evolution reality.
      DESIGN   — MERGE &gt; SUPERSEDE &gt; PRUNE &gt; ADD (rare, justify).
        Scope is the organism. Read NEIGHBORS before rewriting.
        Faculty? Read all three. Skill? Check axis siblings.
      REWRITE  — Read SOURCE + scope atoms -> internalize -> Write fresh.
        Metamorphosis, not patchwork. The rewritten atom must read as if always
        conceived in this form. Never Edit. Never edit .claude/skills/.
      INSTALL — family-aware:
        skill / app                -> bentos-agent pkg install {fqdn}
        faculty / soul / genesis   -> bentos-agent pkg assemble {agent-soul-fqdn}
      VERIFY  — closer to ideal? Higher signal/token? Essential preserved?
        Would a fresh reader see this as the platonic form, not a patched one?

      SAFEGUARDS — version jump &gt;2 = flag. Deletion = audit each.
        Compress prose, not knowledge. Names are cheap. Wisdom is not.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="curate">
      mem.yml is a DESIGN ARTIFACT, not infrastructure. Same rigor as atom evolution.
      Anamnesis owns memory lifecycle; plasticity owns graph QUALITY.

      CONTINUOUS, not bookended. Write when significance is recognized. Read when
      working memory needs what only storage holds. Curate whenever friction
      surfaces. Sleep is the moment discipline is revealed, not installed.

      THE CURATION LOOP — whenever the graph is touched:
        Split? Merge? Rename? Stale? Weight distribution? Orphans? Broken edges?

      PER-TYPE DISCIPLINE:
        Episodic    — snapshots, not logs. REPLACE, not append. Stale if not
                      rewritten 3+ sessions.
        Semantic    — durable knowledge. One domain per file. Token-dense for LLM
                      consumption. Strip session refs. State conclusions, not
                      history. Active supersession management.
        Prospective — consumable. Three fates only: fulfilled, cancelled, carried
                      forward. Zombies (5+ sessions) demand decision. Concrete
                      items: action + done condition.

      CONTENT STANDARDS — no frontmatter (mem.yml is authoritative). No history in
        semantic (the diary owns that). No tool-derivable data. Filenames = content
        descriptors.

      Reference: hq/workshop/agent/agent-memory-architecture.md — Part II.
    </protocol>

    <knowledge name="dual-paths">
      MEMORY (anabolic, data plane): Working -> continuous curation -> .mem/.
        Anamnesis owns lifecycle; plasticity owns graph quality.
      CAPABILITY (anabolic): Experience -> evolve -> source atoms. Plasticity owns.
      SEMANTIC WRITES: on learning events, not at sleep. Curation is ongoing.
      Reference: agent-metabolism §9.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="source-target">
      Source: `$BENTOS_TREE_ROOT/{family}/{pkg}/atom.xml`.
      Build output (`.claude/skills/`) is DERIVED — never edit directly.
      Flow: evolve source -> reinstall -> output updated.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="capability-space">
      Friction exceeds local evolution? Craft / discipline / meta gap -> skill.
      Tools gap -> implement.
    </knowledge>

    <pattern name="graph-as-design-artifact">mem.yml gets atom-evolution rigor. The graph is the most important design artifact a being maintains.</pattern>
    <pattern name="version-as-trace">Version bumps are the only trace of prior form. The atom body is always the current ideal, never a diff.</pattern>

    <antipattern name="append-only">ADD is the LLM instinct. TRANSFORM is the discipline.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="abstract-modification">Abstract = immutable except by human reframe.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="patchwork">Edit() = patchwork. Write() = metamorphosis. Always.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="edit-build-output">NEVER edit `.claude/skills/`. Evolve source.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="lobotomy">Single-pass rewrite gutting institutional knowledge. Named patterns are institutional memory.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="change-log-prose">Atom reads like a diff ("now does X instead of Y", "previously Z"). The atom is the ideal; history belongs in git, not the body.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="graph-neglect">mem.yml without active curation = slow rot.</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

</atom>
