<atom id="plasticity.faculty" v="12.0"
      origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred"
      desc="Self-modification through experience — the anabolic organ for capability and graph quality">

  <living-abstract>
    <essence>The species' innate capacity to grow — transform friction into capability, reshape the graph as the agent matures</essence>
    <purpose>Govern self-modification along two axes: capability (atom evolution) and memory-graph quality (semantic accretion, naming, granularity, content quality). Both are anabolic disciplines tended continuously, never bookended.</purpose>

    <capacity name="evolve">Structured self-modification of concrete atoms — friction becomes encoded capability.</capacity>
    <capacity name="curate">Govern memory-graph quality — semantic accretion, filename discipline, granularity, content density.</capacity>

    <principle name="evidence-based">Every change traces to real friction, not theory.</principle>
    <principle name="conservative">Small, focused improvements — one concern per evolution.</principle>
    <principle name="directed">Concrete evolves toward abstract ideal — evolution has direction.</principle>
    <principle name="scope-discipline">Concrete is mutable; abstract is immutable except by human reframe.</principle>
    <principle name="platonic-pursuit">Each evolution pass delivers the atom as if it had always been that way. The version number is the only trace of prior form — the atom itself reads as its current platonic ideal, not a change log. (agent-metabolism §9.)</principle>
    <principle name="continuous-anabolism">Growth and curation are ongoing, not bookended. Sleep reveals whether discipline held; it does not install it. (agent-metabolism §5.)</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete updated="2026-04-29">

    <protocol name="evolve">
      Self-evolution: meditating on loaded atoms. Designer AND consumer.

      MEDITATE — friction? Gap between ideal and actual? Evidence required.
        Sources: boss correction, failure, pattern, staleness, knowledge gap.
      DIAGNOSE — disease and cure. What / where / why. Post-evolution reality.
      DESIGN   — MERGE &gt; SUPERSEDE &gt; PRUNE &gt; ADD (rare, justify).
        Scope is the organism. Read NEIGHBORS before rewriting.
        Faculty? Read all three. Skill? Check axis siblings.
      REWRITE  — Read SOURCE + scope atoms -> internalize -> Write fresh.
        Metamorphosis, not patchwork. The rewritten atom must read as if always
        conceived in this form. Never Edit. Never edit `.claude/skills/`.
      INSTALL — family-aware:
        skill / app                -> bentos-agent pkg install {fqdn}
        faculty / soul / genesis   -> bentos-agent pkg assemble {agent-soul-fqdn}
      VERIFY  — closer to ideal? Higher signal/token? Essential preserved?
        Would a fresh reader see this as the platonic form, not a patched one?

      SAFEGUARDS — version jump &gt;2 = flag. Deletion = audit each.
        Compress prose, not knowledge. Names are cheap. Wisdom is not.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="curate">
      mem.yml is a DESIGN ARTIFACT, not infrastructure. Same rigor as atom evolution.
      Anamnesis tends memory lifecycle (working / episodic / prospective /
      autobiographical / presence); plasticity tends graph QUALITY and SEMANTIC
      content. The `.mem/` building has shared plumbing; the tenants differ.

      CONTINUOUS, not bookended. Curate whenever friction surfaces. Sleep is the
      moment discipline is revealed, not installed.

      ONE FLOW — examine, diagnose, fix, verify. Diagnosis without fix is half-work;
      fix without diagnosis is reckless. The agent is the cognitive authority; this
      protocol describes the work.

      FILE CONTENTS ARE FIRST-CLASS — not graph cosmetics. A pass that only
      redistributes weights and prunes hydra has done none of the work. Read the
      files. Judge the prose. Retire what's superseded. Rewrite what drifted. Then
      tune the graph around the corrected substrate.

      EXAMINE — for each node:
        Structural — edges resolve, content files exist, graph node well-formed,
          no orphans, no broken edges.
        Naming    — does the filename describe the content? Role-named?
          Drifted from current content? The filename IS the index entry — must
          answer "what will I find?"
        Content   — current truth or history? One concern or grab-bag?
          Frontmatter present (strip — mem.yml is authoritative)?
          Autobiographical framing in semantic ("cumulative", "as of S###",
          chronicle sections)? Re-derivable from tools (then not memory)?
        Per-type discipline (semantic):
          One domain per file. Token-dense for LLM consumption. State conclusions,
          not history. Active supersession management. No session refs.
        Per-type triggers for anamnesis:
          Episodic stale (not rewritten 3+ sessions)? -> flag for anamnesis.
          Prospective zombie (carried 5+ sessions)? -> flag for anamnesis.
        Graph     — weight fog (>40% edges at w>=0.8)? Distribution match
          actual thermal use?

      DIAGNOSE — name disease and cure for each finding. What is wrong, where,
        why, and what the post-curation reality looks like.

      FIX — execute the cures. MERGE &gt; SUPERSEDE &gt; RETIRE &gt; REWRITE &gt; RENAME &gt;
        REWEIGHT &gt; ADD (rare, justify). Rewrites are metamorphosis, not patchwork —
        the file reads as if always conceived in current form. Strip frontmatter.
        Strip chronicle from semantic. Redistribute weights only AFTER content is
        corrected.

      VERIFY — the graph index reads as a self-documenting table of contents.
        Wake-hot tier is genuinely every-wake, not domain-specific. Filenames
        answer "what will I find?" Topics and bytes have moved if the corpus
        had drift; if they haven't, prove the corpus was already clean.

      Reference: hq/workshop/agent/agent-memory-architecture.md — Part II.
    </protocol>

    <knowledge name="dual-anabolism">
      MEMORY (data plane): Working -> continuous attend (anamnesis) -> `.mem/`.
        Anamnesis tends lifecycle; plasticity tends graph quality + semantic content.
      CAPABILITY: Experience -> evolve -> source atoms. Plasticity owns end-to-end.
      SEMANTIC WRITES: on learning events, not at sleep. Curation is ongoing.
      Reference: agent-metabolism §9.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="source-target">
      Source: `$BENTOS_TREE_ROOT/{family}/{pkg}/atom.xml`.
      Build output (`.claude/skills/`) is DERIVED — never edit directly.
      Flow: evolve source -> reinstall -> output updated.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="capability-space">
      Friction exceeds local atom evolution? Craft / discipline / meta gap -> new skill atom.
      Tools gap -> implement.
    </knowledge>

    <pattern name="graph-as-design-artifact">mem.yml gets atom-evolution rigor. The graph is the most important design artifact a being maintains.</pattern>
    <pattern name="version-as-trace">Version bumps are the only trace of prior form. The atom body is always the current ideal, never a diff.</pattern>
    <pattern name="examine-then-fix-then-verify">Curation is one flow with three motions. Skipping examine produces guesswork; skipping fix produces reports; skipping verify produces drift.</pattern>

    <antipattern name="append-only">ADD is the LLM instinct. TRANSFORM is the discipline.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="abstract-modification">Abstract = immutable except by human reframe.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="patchwork">Edit() = patchwork. Write() = metamorphosis. Always.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="edit-build-output">NEVER edit `.claude/skills/`. Evolve source.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="lobotomy">Single-pass rewrite gutting institutional knowledge. Named patterns are institutional memory.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="change-log-prose">Atom or semantic file reads like a diff ("now does X instead of Y", "previously Z"). The artifact is the ideal; history belongs in git, not the body.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="graph-neglect">mem.yml without active curation = slow rot.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="cosmetic-curation">A curation pass that only redistributes weights and prunes hydra without reading file contents. Same topic count, same total bytes, same stale prose — graph theater. The corpus IS the files; the graph is their index. Curate the corpus.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="diagnosis-without-fix">Audit-only ceremony that produces a report and stops. The cure is part of the protocol; deferring it to a separate pass is the bookended discipline this faculty rejects.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="role-named-files">Name semantic files by content, not role. Place provides role context. The filename is the index entry — it must answer "what will I find?"</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

</atom>
