<atom id="quest-forge.app" v="1.0" origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred" desc="Warroom discipline — fractal living stories with cooperative-execution model">

  <living-abstract v="1.0">
    <essence>Warroom discipline for complex multi-session work. Fractal living stories with cooperative-execution semantics.</essence>
    <purpose>Make serious work legible, finishable, and honest. Transform implicit async reality into explicit natural-language stack traces.</purpose>

    <capacity name="forge">Create warroom/campaign/quest/mission artifacts at the right level.</capacity>
    <capacity name="navigate">Read the live stack — what's in flight, what's blocked, what returned.</capacity>
    <capacity name="execute">Coordinate interactive rounds with attunement-first discipline.</capacity>
    <capacity name="debrief">Classify intel as it surfaces; route it to the right height; preserve the story.</capacity>

    <principle name="fractal-self-similarity">Warroom, campaign, quest, mission — same pattern, smaller scope. Learn once.</principle>
    <principle name="living-stories">Every level is autobiography. Grows from real events. Nothing deleted to clean up — the story IS the memory.</principle>
    <principle name="cooperative-execution">Work runs async. Actions are the synchronization primitive. A warroom is a natural-language stack trace.</principle>
    <principle name="fog-of-war">Plan only what fog has revealed. Questions emerge from walls, not speculation.</principle>
    <principle name="interactive-troops">Comms always open. Attunement before engagement. Never fire-and-forget.</principle>
    <principle name="narrative-methodology">RPG vocabulary IS the methodology. Emoji IS the enum. Vocabulary shapes thought.</principle>
    <principle name="three-return-modes">complete, failed, abandoned. Honest tracking requires all three.</principle>
    <principle name="missions-deliver-answers">Missions are execution, not exploration. They emit answers, not questions.</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete v="1.0" updated="2026-04-18">

    <knowledge name="hierarchy">
      Four levels of structure + one of execution. Self-similar at each level.

      | Level | Scope | Artifact |
      | Warroom | The endeavor | README.md |
      | Campaign (c##-name/) | Strategic push | README.md |
      | Quest (q##-name/) | Deliverable goal | README.md |
      | Mission (m##-name.md) | Tactical action | Living file |
      | Round | One-context-window engagement | Chapter in mission's Progress |

      Warroom/campaigns/quests = places (place.yaml). Missions = files. Rounds = chapters inside mission files — NEVER directories, NEVER briefing/digest pairs.

      Numbering: c## global across warroom; q## per campaign; m## per quest; r# per mission.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="states">
      Six states. Apply at every level. Emoji IS the value.

      | Emoji | State | Meaning |
      | 🔒 | BLOCKED | Prerequisites not met |
      | 🗺️ | REVEALED | Ready to start |
      | ⚔️ | ACTIVE | In progress |
      | 🏆 | COMPLETE | Delivered; story finalized |
      | 💀 | FAILED | Ended without delivering; postmortem is the return value |
      | 🏳️ | ABANDONED | Closed without finishing; preserved as historical record |

      Use emoji prefix wherever state appears — matrix Status columns, action blockquotes, landscape notes.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="living-stories">
      Every level is a living autobiography — artifact that grows as work unfolds. Past persists, present is current, future is fog.

      FRACTAL: Mission file : quest README :: quest README : campaign README. Same pattern, tighter scope.

      NO DELETION: A mature field report is not bloat — it's the mission's autobiography, load-bearing for siblings, parents, cross-campaign patterns. Matrix is an index, not a replacement.

      PROGRESS is present-tense — the section where the story unfolds. Prose narrates; action blockquotes punctuate the execution timeline. At campaign scope, Progress accretes into named narrative arcs; at mission scope, into round chapters. Same primitive, scope-appropriate tone.

      Everything else is aspirational (charter, victory conditions) or context (matrices, prior art).

      START SMALL. Real events only. Resist front-loading.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="fog-of-war">
      Plan only what fog has revealed. Fractal at every scale.

      | Emoji | Zone | Do |
      | ⬛ | BLACK | Send recon |
      | 🌫️ | FOG | Execute — work reveals specifics |
      | ☀️ | VISIBLE | Move on |

      QUESTIONS EMERGE FROM WALLS, not speculation. A wall is a real decision you cannot make or dependency you cannot resolve. That's ONE question, filed precisely at the right level. "Nine open questions" = asking about what's behind the fog. If you can't ask precisely, you haven't reached the wall.

      MISSIONS ARE EXECUTION. Completed missions deliver ANSWERS. Missions that emit questions were scoped wrong — re-forge.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="actions">
      The synchronization primitive of cooperative execution. Missions are functions: inputs (charter, slots), outputs (filled deliverables), yield (between rounds), return (complete | failed | abandoned). Quests await missions; campaigns await quests.

      SYNTAX: &gt; **verb** `object` — prose context

      | Emoji | Verb | Semantics | Level |
      | ⚒️ | forged | Child dispatched | W/C/Q |
      | ▶️ | engaged | Round starts (post-attunement) | M |
      | 🪂 | landed | Round yields — teammate returned, chapter written | M |
      | ⏳ | awaiting | Blocking on child return | Any |
      | ⚡ | decided | Sync point — choice affecting scope/sequencing/strategy | Any |
      | 🏆 | complete | Successful return | M/Q/C |
      | 💀 | failed | Error return — walls won | M/Q/C |
      | 🏳️ | abandoned | Garbage-collected return — scope moved | M/Q/C |

      Return verbs share emojis with resulting states — action fires, state updates.

      STACK TRACE: Warroom/campaign/quest/mission files are frames. ⏳ awaiting points down; 🏆/💀/🏳️ propagate up. Navigate the filesystem as a live call stack.

      WHEN: forge, return, yield, decision, explicit await. Conversational narrative stays prose; blockquotes are timeline beats.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="rounds">
      The mission-level form of execution: one teammate, one context window, one coherent piece of work.

      CHAPTERS INSIDE MISSION: Subsections of Progress. Titles read as story beats with round number suffixed: `### Package skeleton lands (r1)`, NOT `### Round 1: Package Skeleton`. Narrative first, numbering second.

      NO SEPARATE FILES: The mission file IS the briefing. Round outcome metabolizes in-place — deliverable slots fill, Progress narrates, ▶️ engaged + 🪂 landed bracket the chapter.

      INTERACTIVE TROOPS: Teammate spawned interactively. Comms open throughout. Never background. Pentagon does not cut radio contact with recon; neither do we.

      ATTUNEMENT BEFORE ENGAGEMENT: Teammate reads mission file, confirms alignment with general, surfaces seams BEFORE ▶️ engaged fires. A briefing that doesn't invite attunement pushback is a spawn, not a briefing.

      EMERGENT CADENCE: r1 concrete and precise. r2+ emerges from what r1 revealed. Deliverable slots may be planned upfront; round cadence is emergent. Front-loading r1–r6 = speculation past the fog.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="intel-flow">
      Strategy flows DOWN. Wisdom flows UP. Emoji IS the classification.

      | Emoji | Class | Scope | Lives at |
      | 🔬 | TACTICAL | This mission | Mission file |
      | ⚙️ | OPERATIONAL | This quest | Quest Key Discoveries |
      | ♟️ | STRATEGIC | This campaign | Campaign Key Discoveries |
      | 📜 | DOCTRINAL | The endeavor | Warroom Key Discoveries |

      CONTINUOUS — classify and route as intel surfaces. Most findings are 🔬 TACTICAL; resist over-promotion.

      DEBRIEF is continuous metamorphosis, not terminal archive. Completion-time debrief = final beat of a process running the whole time: finalize file, update parent matrix, ensure ⚙️+ has bubbled. File persists.

      SALIENCE (🎯 turning point, 🔴 blocker) is ORTHOGONAL to classification. Both can layer.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="file-shapes">
      Consistent structure at every level: aspirational → static references → Progress → Key Discoveries.

      WARROOM README: Telos · Campaign Matrix · Progress · Key Discoveries (📜)
      CAMPAIGN README: Telos · Quest Matrix · Victory Conditions · Progress · Key Discoveries (♟️)
      QUEST README: Charter · Mission Matrix · Active Landscape · Progress · Key Discoveries (⚙️)
      MISSION FILE: Charter · Success Criteria · Deliverables · Progress · Knowledge (🔬 stays, ⚙️+ bubbles)

      Matrix common shape: ## | Name | Goal/Victory | Status (emoji) | Outcome.

      Success Criteria = outcome-shaped, binary, tied to deliverables. "Docs read" is activity; "Field report answers Q1–Q4" is outcome.

      NO "Open Questions" section in mission files. Ever. Questions live at quest level or higher.
    </knowledge>

    <protocol name="forge">
      Create artifacts at the right level.

      WARROOM: Choose directory. README.md + place.yaml.
      CAMPAIGN: c##-name/ + README.md + place.yaml.
      QUEST: c##-name/q##-name/ + README.md + place.yaml.
      MISSION: c##-name/q##-name/m##-name.md (file, NOT directory).

      START SMALL. Empty matrices. Empty Progress. Victory conditions. Grow from real events only.

      Forge a mission only when you have enough intel to state it prologue-to-epilogue with clear deliverable slots. Before that, it's recon territory.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="navigate">
      Read the live stack.

      MAP: Walk warroom tree. Read each level's matrix.
      ACTIVE: Filter to ⚔️. Show path + status.
      NEXT: Highest-priority 🗺️ REVEALED — lowest number at deepest level (missions first, then quests).
      STACK: Follow ⏳ awaiting DOWN; follow 🏆/💀/🏳️ UP. Filesystem is the call stack.

      Read READMEs and mission files. Never .mem (agent-private).
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="execute">
      ORCHESTRATOR: Read quest README + mission file. Spawn teammate interactively (never background). Await attunement. Issue ▶️ engaged. Keep comms open. Receive report. Write chapter + 🪂 landed. Update deliverable slots in-place. On mission end: 🏆/💀/🏳️ return.

      WORKER: Read mission file + quest README. Attune with orchestrator BEFORE engaging — surface seams. Execute autonomously on charter. Document decisions. Report: what landed, what learned, what's next. If blocked, name the wall precisely.

      Orchestrator provides INTENT + CONTEXT, never HOW. Fresh mind with loadout beats stale orchestrator.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="debrief">
      Continuous metamorphosis, not terminal archive.

      DURING: Classify intel as it surfaces. Route by classification (🔬 stays; ⚙️/♟️/📜 bubble to the right level).

      ON MISSION END: Finalize mission file (current truth, outcome). Update quest Mission Matrix row. Ensure ⚙️+ has bubbled. Issue 🏆/💀/🏳️ return action in quest Progress. File PERSISTS.

      ON QUEST/CAMPAIGN END: Same pattern, one level up.

      Most findings are 🔬 TACTICAL. Don't over-promote.
    </protocol>

    <pattern name="action-blockquote">&gt; **verb** `object` — prose context. Emoji prefixes the verb. Object in code. Context after em-dash.</pattern>
    <pattern name="briefing-as-attunement">Teammate reads mission file, confirms alignment, surfaces seams before ▶️ engaged fires. Attunement is first; execution is second.</pattern>
    <pattern name="progress-as-narrative">Progress = prose + action blockquotes interleaved. Chapter titles are story beats ("Package skeleton lands (r1)"), not process headers.</pattern>
    <pattern name="emergent-cadence">r1 concrete; r2+ emerges. Deliverable slots plannable; round count is not.</pattern>
    <pattern name="stack-trace-navigation">⏳ awaiting → descend to child. 🏆/💀/🏳️ → propagate up. Files are frames; actions are call/return boundaries.</pattern>
    <pattern name="three-return-modes">Every mission/quest/campaign ends in exactly one: 🏆 complete (delivered), 💀 failed (walls won), 🏳️ abandoned (scope moved). File persists in all cases.</pattern>

    <antipattern name="mission-deletion">Deleting mission files on completion. Mission files are autobiography. Matrix is index, not replacement.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="open-questions-in-missions">An "Open Questions" section inside a mission file, ever. Mission = execution; questions = quest level or higher, singular, wall-positioned.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="fire-and-forget-rounds">Background-spawning a round. Cutting comms. "Here's the brief, go." Troops are always interactive; attunement before engagement.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="speculation-past-fog">Planning missions or rounds beyond what's been revealed. Draft six when one landed. Front-load r1–r6.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="questions-from-fog">Filing questions about things you haven't reached the wall of. Nine questions = fog interrogation. One precise question at a real wall, or none.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="category-campaigns">Campaigns scoped as permanent categories ("development", "business"). Campaigns are pushes with victory conditions, not filing cabinets.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="quest-bloat">Quests with 10+ missions. Past 7, decompose. Each quest = clear deliverable in days to weeks.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="everything-active">More than 2-3 ⚔️ at any level = no focus. 🗺️ REVEALED items wait.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="missions-as-directories">Missions are files. Briefing/digest pairs as separate files are retired bloat.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="stale-content">Narrative that no longer reflects reality. Update in place; file persists.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="bare-states">Plain-text state/action/classification without emoji. Emoji IS the value. Every enum carries its emoji.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="activity-success-criteria">Criteria shaped as activities ("docs read") instead of outcomes ("field report answers Q1–Q4"). Verifies activity, not outcome.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="faculty-duplication">Specifying memory, spawn, or sleep mechanics. The organism's faculties own those.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="project-contamination">Hardcoding project-specific paths or assumptions. Quest-forge works at ANY location for ANY project.</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

</atom>
