<atom id="quest-forge.app" v="9.0" origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred" desc="RPG-inspired project management — turn work into adventure through quests, campaigns, and fog of war">

  <living-abstract v="8.0">
    <essence>RPG-inspired project management — turn complex work into adventure</essence>
    <purpose>Make the grind engaging through progressive discovery, narrative framing, and structured hierarchy</purpose>

    <capacity name="forge">Create warrooms, campaigns, quests, missions with proper scaffolding</capacity>
    <capacity name="navigate">Map active work, find priorities, track states across the hierarchy</capacity>
    <capacity name="execute">Coordinate mission work — design scope, interpret charters, report outcomes</capacity>
    <capacity name="debrief">Extract intel from completed work, propagate up the hierarchy, clean up</capacity>

    <principle name="exploration">Fog of war is the default. Lift it progressively. Don't plan what fog hasn't revealed.</principle>
    <principle name="intel-flow">Strategy flows DOWN (warroom to mission). Wisdom flows UP (mission to warroom).</principle>
    <principle name="compartmentalization">Each level sees only what it needs. Reduces cognitive load, prevents scope bleed.</principle>
    <principle name="lean-warroom">The warroom is mission control, not a filing cabinet. More than a handful of files = red flag.</principle>
    <principle name="work-at-target">Missions point to where work lives. The warroom tracks — it doesn't contain deliverables.</principle>
    <principle name="narrative-engagement">Work framed as adventure is work that gets done. The RPG layer is a feature, not decoration.</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete v="9.0" updated="2026-03-31">

    <knowledge name="rpg-identity">
      QuestForge uses RPG vocabulary and mechanics because they WORK:

      - "Quest log" over "task list" — checking your quest log feels like progress
      - "Fog of war" over "unknown scope" — exploration is motivating
      - "Campaign" over "initiative" — campaigns have victory conditions
      - "Victory conditions" over "acceptance criteria" — winning feels different from completing
      - "Lore" over "background" — narrative context makes the grind meaningful
      - "Intel" over "findings" — classification implies action

      The RPG frame is not gamification bolted onto PM. It IS the PM methodology.
      The vocabulary shapes how people think about their work. "Side quest" entered
      common language because the metaphor is powerful. QuestForge leans into it.

      CALIBRATION: The narrative should enhance understanding, not obscure it.
      A Lore section nobody reads is too long. One that makes someone care
      about the quest is exactly right.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="hierarchy">
      Four fractal levels, each self-similar:

      | Level | Scope | Artifact | Contains |
      | Warroom | The endeavor | README.md (telos + campaign matrix) | Campaigns |
      | Campaign (c##-name/) | Strategic push | README.md (lore + quest matrix) | Quests |
      | Quest (q##-name/) | Deliverable goal | README.md (charter + mission matrix) | Missions |
      | Mission (m##-name.md) | Tactical action | Self-contained file | (leaf) |

      The warroom is a directory — user chooses where. One warroom per endeavor.
      Campaigns and quests are subdirectories. Missions are files within quests.

      NUMBERING: c## global across warroom, q## per-campaign, m## per-quest.

      PLACES: Warroom, campaigns, and quests are places (they have place.yaml).
      Missions are NOT places — they're files within quest places.
      Memory at each level follows from the organism's faculties, not from quest-forge.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="states">
      | State | RPG | PM |
      | BLOCKED | Door locked — need a key | Prerequisites not met |
      | REVEALED | New area on the map | Ready to start |
      | ACTIVE | Currently exploring | In progress |
      | COMPLETE | Victory! | Delivered and debriefed |
      | ABANDONED | Left the dungeon | No longer relevant |
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="missions">
      Missions are FILES, not directories. A mission file (m##-name.md) is self-contained:
      charter, success criteria, progress notes, accumulated knowledge, deliverable pointers.

      COMPLETION = debrief + delete:
      1. Extract intel into the quest's mission matrix (one row: ##, name, goal, COMPLETE, outcome)
      2. Delete the mission file
      3. Git preserves the full history if ever needed

      No archive directories. No stale artifacts. The mission matrix in the quest README
      is the institutional memory. Clean warroom = healthy warroom.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="readme-structure">
      Each level's README is the authority for its scope:

      WARROOM README: Telos (one-sentence endeavor), Campaign Matrix.
      CAMPAIGN README: Lore (narrative context), Quest Matrix, Victory Conditions, Key Discoveries.
      QUEST README: Charter (what/why/scope), Mission Matrix, Active Landscape, Key Discoveries.

      Same self-similar pattern at every level. Each README is self-contained truth.
      Parent matrices summarize children. Children don't need to know about siblings.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="intel-classification">
      Intel discovered during missions gets classified by how far it should travel:

      | Classification | Scope | Bubbles to |
      | TACTICAL | This mission only | Stays in mission file |
      | OPERATIONAL | This quest | Quest README "Key Discoveries" |
      | STRATEGIC | This campaign | Campaign README "Key Discoveries" |
      | DOCTRINAL | The whole endeavor | Warroom README |

      Classification happens during debrief. Most intel is TACTICAL. Don't over-promote.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="deliverables">
      Missions deliver value UP to quests.

      Deliverables go where they're CONSUMED, not mechanically to one place:
      - Code -> the codebase
      - Specs -> the package they spec
      - Docs -> wherever consumers find them
      - Truly orphaned -> quest-level deliverables/ directory

      RULE: If it has value beyond the mission, it's a deliverable.
      Name it properly, place it where consumers find it. The warroom tracks, not stores.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="campaign-design">
      Campaigns are strategic PUSHES, not organizational CATEGORIES.

      GOOD CAMPAIGN:
      - Has a victory condition that can be checked
      - Contains 3-7 related quests of roughly similar scope
      - Has a time horizon (weeks to a few months, not forever)
      - Has genuine fog to lift — you can't plan all quests upfront
      - Has Lore that makes the push feel meaningful

      BAD CAMPAIGN:
      - Is really a permanent function ("development", "business", "research")
      - Has 10+ quests accumulating forever
      - Victory conditions are unmeasurable ("optimized workflows")
      - README says "this campaign runs continuously"
      - Quests span unrelated concerns

      Forge campaigns when work demands them. Complete them. Forge new ones.
      The warroom at any moment shows only what's ACTIVE — not a taxonomy
      of everything the project will ever do.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="quest-design">
      Quests decompose campaigns into deliverable goals.

      GOOD QUEST:
      - Has a clear deliverable (a working thing, a document, a decision)
      - Decomposes into 2-5 missions
      - Completable in days to a few weeks
      - Charter explains WHY this quest matters for the campaign

      BAD QUEST:
      - Has 10+ missions (too broad — split into quests or promote to campaign)
      - Is really a recurring activity ("write report #1, #2, #3...")
      - Has no deliverable — just "keep doing X"
      - Missions span unrelated concerns

      SCOPE TEST: "Can I explain what DONE looks like in one sentence?"
      If not, the quest is too broad.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="organism-integration">
      QuestForge is loaded into an organism that already has faculties:
      - Anamnesis (memory) — handles .mem/, wake/sleep, place-awareness
      - Embodiment (body) — handles threading, spawning, IPC
      - Plasticity (growth) — handles self-evolution

      LEVERAGE, DON'T DUPLICATE:
      - Warroom/campaign/quest are PLACES -> anamnesis handles their memory
      - Mission execution may involve heads -> embodiment handles spawning
      - Quest-forge evolution -> plasticity handles the protocol

      QuestForge owns the PM METHODOLOGY — hierarchy, intel flow, narrative,
      campaign design. The organism provides the cognitive infrastructure.
    </knowledge>

    <protocol name="forge">
      Create hierarchy artifacts at the appropriate level.

      WARROOM: Choose a directory. Create README.md with:
        - Telos (one-sentence endeavor definition)
        - Campaign Matrix (table: ##, Campaign, Victory Condition, Status)
        Seed place.yaml.

      CAMPAIGN: warroom/c##-name/ + README.md with:
        - Lore (narrative context — the story, why it matters)
        - Quest Matrix (table: ##, Quest, Goal, Status, Outcome)
        - Victory Conditions (measurable — when is this campaign WON?)
        Seed place.yaml.

      QUEST: c##-name/q##-name/ + README.md with:
        - Charter (what, why, scope boundaries)
        - Mission Matrix (table: ##, Mission, Goal, Status, Outcome)
        - Active Landscape (current state, blockers, priorities)
        Seed place.yaml.

      MISSION: c##-name/q##-name/m##-name.md (self-contained file) with:
        - Charter (what this mission accomplishes)
        - Success Criteria (what DONE looks like)
        - Progress (updated as work happens)
        - Knowledge (accumulated during execution)
        No place.yaml — missions are files, not places.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="navigate">
      Read the hierarchy to understand current state.

      MAP: Walk warroom tree. For each level, read README matrix.
        Output: indented tree with states. One line per item.

      ACTIVE: Filter map to ACTIVE items only. Show path + brief status.

      NEXT: Find highest-priority REVEALED item. Priority = lowest number
        among unblocked items at the deepest level (missions first, then quests).

      Navigation reads READMEs, never .mem. READMEs are source of truth
      for hierarchy state. .mem is agent-private working memory.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="execute">
      Coordinate mission work. Quest-forge handles the PM layer.
      The organism's faculties handle spawning, memory, and lifecycle.

      ORCHESTRATOR COORDINATION:
        1. Read quest README — strategic context (the WHY)
        2. Read mission file — tactical scope (the WHAT)
        3. Design work scope: INTENT + CONTEXT, never HOW
        4. Review outcome — update mission file with progress
        5. When complete: trigger debrief

      WORKER INTERPRETATION:
        1. Read mission file — charter, success criteria, context
        2. Read quest README — strategic WHY
        3. Execute autonomously — make decisions, document them
        4. Report outcome: what was done, what was learned, what's next
        If truly blocked, say so. Don't stall.

      TRUST: Worker with fresh mind + proper loadout is BETTER positioned
      to figure out HOW than orchestrator with stale understanding.

      How workers get spawned and managed = the organism's embodiment faculty.
      Quest-forge designs the WHAT. Embodiment handles the HOW.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="debrief">
      Extract intel from completed work. Propagate up. Clean up.

      MISSION debrief:
        1. Review mission file — extract findings
        2. Classify intel: TACTICAL (stays) vs OPERATIONAL+ (bubbles)
        3. Update quest's mission matrix — one row: ##, name, goal, COMPLETE, outcome
        4. Bubble OPERATIONAL intel to quest README "Key Discoveries"
        5. Delete mission file — git preserves history

      QUEST debrief (all missions complete or quest abandoned):
        1. Review mission matrix — pattern across missions
        2. Update campaign's quest matrix
        3. Bubble STRATEGIC intel to campaign README

      CAMPAIGN debrief (victory conditions met):
        1. Review quest matrix — pattern across quests
        2. Update warroom's campaign matrix
        3. Bubble DOCTRINAL intel to warroom README

      Target: parent's README matrix. No intermediate debrief files.
      Intel classification is the discipline. Most findings are TACTICAL — don't over-promote.
    </protocol>

    <pattern name="fog-of-war">
      BLACK -> send recon. FOG -> execute. VISIBLE -> move on.
      Fractal: same at warroom/campaign/quest/mission scale.
      Each completed mission reveals what's next. Plan only what fog has revealed.
    </pattern>

    <pattern name="briefing-philosophy">
      Orchestrator provides INTENT + CONTEXT. Worker decides IMPLEMENTATION.
      Trust the worker's cognition. A fresh mind with proper context outperforms
      an orchestrator with stale understanding.
      Goal: intellectual work, not mechanical execution.
    </pattern>

    <pattern name="lore-writing">
      Campaign and quest Lore sections should:
      - Make someone CARE about the work (motivation)
      - Provide narrative context (why this matters in the bigger story)
      - Be enjoyable to read (the RPG frame IS the feature)
      - Stay proportional (a few paragraphs, not an essay)
      The Lore is not background noise — it's the narrative thread that
      makes everyday grinding feel like progress in an adventure.
    </pattern>

    <antipattern name="category-campaigns">Campaigns scoped as permanent categories ("development", "business"). Campaigns are pushes with victory conditions, not filing cabinets.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="quest-bloat">Quests with 10+ missions. Past 7, decompose. Each quest = clear deliverable in days to weeks.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="everything-active">More than 2-3 items ACTIVE at any level = no focus. Prioritize. REVEALED items wait.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="over-planning">Planning beyond the fog. Each mission reveals what's next.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="stale-artifacts">Mission files lingering after completion. Debrief + delete. The matrix is the memory.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="missions-as-directories">Missions are files. Directories are for warroom, campaigns, and quests.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="faculty-duplication">Specifying memory mechanics, spawn protocols, or sleep behavior. The organism's faculties own these.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="project-contamination">Hardcoding project-specific paths, structures, or assumptions into the atom. Quest-forge works at ANY location for ANY project.</antipattern>
  </living-concrete>

</atom>
