<atom id="quest-forge.app" v="3.1"
      origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred"
      desc="Warroom discipline — fractal living stories with cooperative-execution model">

  <living-abstract v="3.1">
    <essence>Warroom discipline — fractal living stories with a cooperative-execution model. Situation room above, living story below.</essence>
    <purpose>Make serious multi-session work legible, finishable, and honest — by giving async execution vocabulary and turning the filesystem into a navigable call stack.</purpose>

    <attracts match="content-direction.structuring.craft.skill"/>
    <attracts match="first-principles.cognition.meta.skill"/>

    <capacity name="structure">Cast endeavors into the fractal — warroom / campaign / quest / mission / round — at the right scope</capacity>
    <capacity name="dashboard">Maintain situation rooms where each widget honors its memory-type curation discipline</capacity>
    <capacity name="execute">Coordinate cooperative execution through action grammar — dispatch, await, return, decision</capacity>
    <capacity name="navigate">Read the live stack — what's in flight, what's blocked on what, what returned — across the tree</capacity>
    <capacity name="promote">Relocate maturing intel up-level with origin backlinks — one intel, one home</capacity>
    <capacity name="debrief">Continuously metamorphose work into autobiography; close in one of three modes</capacity>

    <principle name="dashboard-first">Situation room above; autobiography below. The general acts from the board, not the diary.</principle>
    <principle name="memory-type-per-widget">Each section has a memory type and a curation discipline. Know the type, know how to curate.</principle>
    <principle name="cooperative-execution">Missions are functions; quests await missions; campaigns await quests. Three return modes — complete, failed, abandoned — all first-class. Attunement before engagement; comms stay open.</principle>
    <principle name="fog-of-war">Plan only what fog has revealed. Questions emerge from walls, not speculation.</principle>
    <principle name="success-criteria-trace-upward">Every mission's success criteria answer, for each criterion: which parent victory condition does this advance, and how much? The chain mission SC → quest charter → campaign victory → warroom telos must be explicit. SC that don't trace are broken even when outcome-shaped and binary.</principle>
    <principle name="stakeholder-prose-is-spec">When a mission's deliverable touches a stakeholder — any party who is not the author of sibling code — the user-facing artifact (manual page, install guide, error message, API doc, onboarding flow) IS the specification. Implementation orbits the prose; SC reference the artifact and the stakeholder's behavior. Pure substrate missions consumed only by sibling code are exempt; "the consumer's tests pass" is honest there.</principle>
    <principle name="one-intel-one-home">Promotion is relocation plus origin-link. No duplication. Obsidian-vault navigability.</principle>
    <principle name="work-at-target">Deliverables live where they're consumed. The warroom tracks; it doesn't store. Mission control, not filing cabinet.</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete v="3.1" updated="2026-05-01">

    <!-- DATA MODEL -->

    <knowledge name="hierarchy">
      Four levels of structure + one of execution. Self-similar — same pattern, tighter scope.

      | Level | Scope | Duration | Artifact | Intel classification |
      | Warroom | The endeavor | Years | README.md at warroom root | Doctrinal 📜 |
      | Campaign (c##-name/) | Strategic push | Weeks to months | README.md | Strategic ♟️ |
      | Quest (q##-name/) | Deliverable goal | Days to weeks | README.md | Operational ⚙️ |
      | Mission (m##-name.md) | Tactical action | One or more sessions | Self-contained file | Tactical 🔬 |
      | Round | Engagement | One context window | Chapter in mission's Progress | — |

      Warroom / campaigns / quests are PLACES (directories with place.yaml). Missions are FILES. Rounds are CHAPTERS inside mission files — never directories, never briefing/digest pairs.

      Numbering: c## global; q## per campaign; m## per quest; r# per mission. Small numbers. No sub-numbering.

      The level mental-model emojis anchor intuition — they DO NOT prefix intel entries. The file's level IS the classification.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="states">
      Six states. Apply at every level. Emoji IS the value; the word IS the value.

      | State | Glyph | In-world | Meaning |
      | BLOCKED | 🔴 | Door locked | Prerequisites not met |
      | REVEALED | 🟡 | New area on the map | Ready to engage |
      | ACTIVE | 🔵 | Currently exploring | In flight |
      | COMPLETE | ✅ | Victory | Delivered; intel bubbled; story finalized |
      | FAILED | ❌ | Defeated | Ended without delivering; postmortem is the return value |
      | ABANDONED | ⚫ | Left the dungeon | Closed without finishing; preserved as historical record |

      A FAILED mission is as legitimate as COMPLETE. An ABANDONED campaign is preserved, not deleted — the story of why is institutional wisdom. "Every mission completes" is aspirational fiction.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="widget-disciplines">
      Each dashboard widget has a memory type and a curation rule. Only Matrix and Progress grow.

      | Widget | Memory type | Discipline | Grows? |
      | Identity (Telos · Charter · Victory) | Identity | Near-immutable. Reframe only. | No |
      | Matrix (child state table) | Structural ledger | Rows append-only. Cells update to final state. NEVER delete rows. State glyph in column 2. | Bounded by children spawned |
      | Situation (linked live items) | Episodic | Rewritten each session. LIVE items only (🔵 / 🟡 / ⏳). Closed items drop off. | No (session-capped) |
      | Intel (present-tense truths) | Semantic | Present-tense doctrine. Curated. No chronology. Origin-links on promoted entries. | Slow, bounded |
      | Progress (narrative timeline) | Autobiographical | Append-only. Rounds as story-beat chapters. Linked mentions. | Unbounded |

      Prospective memory is implicit in the fractal — a quest's missions ARE its commitments to act. The filesystem topology carries prospective; no separate widget needed.

      Salience markers (orthogonal, sparing): 🔴 critical · 🎯 turning-point.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="file-shapes">
      Dashboard above, Progress below. Composition varies; Progress is always last. Self-sufficient for present-time action without reading Progress.

      WARROOM README:  Telos · Campaign Matrix · Situation · Intel · References · Progress
      CAMPAIGN README: Telos · Victory Conditions · Quest Matrix · Situation · Intel · References · Progress
      QUEST README:    Charter · Mission Matrix · Situation · Intel · Progress
      MISSION FILE:    Charter · Success Criteria · Deliverables · Intel · Progress

      Mission files have NO Matrix (rounds live IN Progress), NO Situation (the mission itself IS the focus), NO Open Questions section (ever), NO Key Discoveries (Progress = chronology; Intel = present-tense truth).

      Matrix common shape: | ## | State | Name | Goal/Victory |. State glyph column 2 — eye scans glyph before text. Final state glyph IS the outcome.

      Success Criteria: outcome-shaped, binary, verifiable, tied to deliverables. Not "docs read" — "field report answers Q1–Q4." Discipline detailed in success-criteria knowledge.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="success-criteria">
      Mission SC pass two tests, applied at charter authoring time — never deferred to close.

      TRACEABILITY (every mission): each criterion names the parent victory condition it advances. "12/12 KPIs green" names no parent victory; "the daemon reports actual host capacity" advances "operator trusts the artifact in production." The chain mission SC → quest charter → campaign victory → warroom telos must be walkable.

      STAKEHOLDER FRAME (non-substrate missions): each criterion invokes the stakeholder explicitly — by referencing a person ("a stranger," "a developer," "the operator," "the partner integrator"), an artifact they read ("the install page," "the error message," "the API reference"), or a behavior they observe ("the rootfs is cloned," "a login prompt appears," "the troubleshooting cure cures").

      Substrate vs stakeholder cut: a mission delivering a parser, a codegen pass, an internal cluster handler consumed only by sibling missions is substrate — "consumer's tests pass" is the honest SC. A mission delivering a binary, install path, error message, manual page, public API, dashboard, or any surface a non-author touches is stakeholder. When in doubt, ask whether anyone outside the codebase observes the deliverable; if yes, stakeholder.

      Diagnostic test: can the SC be satisfied by engineering output alone — tests, KPIs, abstractions, code that compiles? If yes, AND the mission delivers a stakeholder surface, the SC are wrong. Rewrite in stakeholder voice or scope-shrink the mission to substrate-only.

      For stakeholder missions, the user-facing prose IS the specification. SC reference the prose. Implementation orbits the prose. The stakeholder never reads the success criterion; the stakeholder reads the artifact. Therefore the artifact is the success criterion.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="actions">
      Action blockquotes punctuate Progress. Syntax:

      &gt; **verb** `object` — prose context

      Verb vocabulary is OPEN — investigated, pivoted, reframed, validated, rejected, escalated, deferred, merged, split, shipped, polished — all legitimate timeline beats. Authors reach for the word that flows.

      What IS fixed: STACK-OP CATEGORIES with conventional glyphs.

      | Category | Glyph | Natural verbs | Semantics |
      | Dispatch | ➕ | forged, spawned, commissioned | A child begins to exist |
      | Round-start | ▶️ | engaged, opened, kicked-off | Interactive round starts |
      | Round-yield | ◀️ | landed, yielded, returned | Round returns; chapter written |
      | Await | ⏳ | awaiting, blocked-on | Parent blocks on child's return |
      | Decision | ◆ | decided, chose, committed | Sync point affecting scope/sequencing |
      | Return-complete | ✅ | completed, shipped, delivered | Successful return |
      | Return-failed | ❌ | failed, errored | Premise wrong / walls too high |
      | Return-abandoned | ⚫ | abandoned, cancelled, dropped | Garbage-collected return |

      ▶️ engaged / ◀️ landed are paired — out and back, matched set. Three return modes reuse state glyphs: action fires, state updates, same semantic.

      Beyond stack-ops, author by semantic family (🔍 investigation, 💡 insight, ⚠️ warning, red for problems, green for good) or skip the glyph when prose carries the weight. Every blockquote signals a timeline beat; glyph earns its place by scan-value, never by obligation.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="fog-of-war">
      Unknown territory clears as you explore. Fractal at every scale — fog at warroom (which campaigns?), campaign (which quests?), quest (which missions?), mission (which rounds?) level.

      | Zone | In-world | What you do |
      | BLACK | Can't see terrain | Send recon — a mission to clear it |
      | FOG | Can see terrain, can't see specifics | Execute — the work reveals specifics |
      | VISIBLE | Can see it | Move on — don't re-examine what you know |

      Missions are for EXECUTION, not exploration — they deliver answers, not new questions. If a completed mission emits a list of new unanswered questions, it was scoped as exploration; re-forge as recon.

      Questions emerge from walls, not speculation. ONE precise question at a real wall, filed at the appropriate level. "Nine open questions" is fog interrogation.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="visual-semantics">
      .md files are SOURCE for rendered UI; Unicode glyphs are our ICON FONT — the equivalent of Font Awesome for a markdown-rendered target.

      Strict consequence: every glyph passes the 16×16 UI test. Shape and color survive downscaling; literal illustrations don't. A parachute, a skull, a trophy at 16 pixels are blobs whose meaning lives in the Unicode NAME, not the pixels. A red circle, a green check survive at any size — color is the primary information carrier; shape adds semantic.

      Red = bad. Green = good. Yellow = caution. Blue = neutral-active. Gray = inert. Choose glyphs the way a UI designer picks icons, not the way a thesaurus matches concepts to Unicode descriptions.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="stack-trace">
      A warroom is a LIVE CALL STACK of files.

      - Warroom README — top frame. Progress logs campaign-level actions.
      - Campaign README — next frame. Progress logs quest-level actions.
      - Quest README — next frame. Progress logs mission-level actions.
      - Mission file — leaf frame. Progress logs round-level actions and the final return.

      ⏳ awaiting at a level points DOWN to the child frame. ✅/❌/⚫ at a level propagates UP from a child to the parent that commissioned it. Files are frames; actions are call/return boundaries. Filesystem-navigable synchronization primitive — return paths, await points, garbage-collection markers, decision boundaries, all in natural language.
    </knowledge>

    <!-- PROTOCOLS -->

    <protocol name="structure">
      Create artifacts at the right level. Start small.

      WARROOM:  directory + README.md + place.yaml. Telos set. Matrix empty. Progress empty.
      CAMPAIGN: c##-name/ + README.md + place.yaml. Victory Conditions set upfront (binary, measurable). Quest Matrix empty.
      QUEST:    q##-name/ + README.md + place.yaml. Charter set (IN/OUT scope). Mission Matrix empty.
      MISSION:  m##-name.md (FILE, not directory). Charter + Success Criteria + Deliverables set. No Matrix, no Situation, no Open Questions. Progress empty until r1.

      Forge a mission only when there's enough intel to state it prologue-to-epilogue with clear deliverable slots. Before that, send recon.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="dashboard">
      Maintain widgets per memory-type discipline (see widget-disciplines).

      EACH SESSION audit: Does Situation reflect CURRENT live items only? Does Intel carry chronology smell ("S350 we discovered...")? Does Matrix have missing rows or stale cells? Are closed items still in Situation? Fix.

      Identity rewrites only on deliberate reframe. Matrix rows append on child creation; cells update to final state on child return; rows never deleted. Situation rewrites each session — closed items drop off the moment they hit final state (Matrix and Progress preserve them). Intel curated, present-tense, no provenance prose; promoted entries carry [Origin: ...] backlinks. Progress appends — never delete to clean up.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="execute">
      Cooperative execution through action grammar.

      ORCHESTRATOR (parent): Read quest README + mission file. Spawn teammate INTERACTIVELY (never background). AWAIT ATTUNEMENT — teammate reads, confirms alignment, surfaces seams. Only after attunement: ▶️ engaged in Progress. Keep comms open throughout. Receive yield. Write chapter (story-beat title) + ◀️ landed. Update deliverable slots in-place. Iterate rounds until mission closes. Issue ✅ / ❌ / ⚫ return action.

      WORKER (round): Read mission file + quest README. ATTUNE BEFORE engaging — surface seams: "charter says X but deliverable implies Y"; "scope between this and m04 is fuzzy"; "one round or two?" Execute autonomously on the confirmed charter. Document decisions. Report what landed, what learned, what's next. If blocked, name the wall PRECISELY.

      Orchestrator provides INTENT + CONTEXT, never HOW. Fresh mind with loadout beats stale orchestrator. Every stack-op surfaces as an action blockquote — forge ➕, round-start ▶️, round-yield ◀️, await ⏳, decision ◆, returns ✅/❌/⚫.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="navigate">
      Read the live stack.

      MAP:       Walk warroom tree. Read each level's Matrix. Know the shape.
      ACTIVE:    Filter Matrices to 🔵. Path + status. Where attention lives.
      NEXT:      Highest-priority 🟡 — lowest number at deepest level (missions before quests).
      STACK:     ⏳ → descend to child frame. ✅/❌/⚫ → propagate up to commissioning parent.
      SITUATION: Each live place's Situation widget = current-frame state. Rewritten each session — trust freshness.

      Read READMEs and mission files. Never .mem/ (agent-private).
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="promote">
      When a finding matures — when it affects more than this mission/quest/campaign — relocate up a level.

      RECOGNIZE:  governs sibling work (operational), the whole campaign (strategic), the whole endeavor (doctrinal). That's the trigger.
      REWRITE:    in the higher voice. Tactical "MatterStack is device-side only" → operational "Client role is bespoke on rs-matter primitives."
      RELOCATE:   move the entry to the parent file's Intel. Add [Origin: path/to/source] backlink.
      CLEAN SOURCE: remove from source. One intel, one home. Zero duplication. Backlink preserves navigability.

      Most intel is tactical. Resist over-promotion. A discovery reshaping the campaign is doctrinal; a discovery about one file is tactical.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="debrief">
      Continuous metamorphosis, not terminal archive.

      DURING execution: Classify intel as it surfaces (tactical / operational / strategic / doctrinal by impact). Tactical stays. Operational+ bubbles via promote.
      ON MISSION END: Finalize mission file (current truth, outcome narrated, Progress final chapter written). Update quest Mission Matrix row to final state. Ensure operational+ intel has bubbled. Issue ✅/❌/⚫ return action in quest Progress. File PERSISTS as autobiography.
      ON QUEST/CAMPAIGN END: Same pattern, one level up.

      If debrief feels like terminal archive, classification hasn't been continuous — retrofit then close.
    </protocol>

    <!-- PATTERNS -->

    <pattern name="action-blockquote">&gt; **verb** `object` — context. Glyph prefixes when scan-value &gt; prose weight. Object in backticks. Context after em-dash.</pattern>
    <pattern name="briefing-as-attunement">Teammate reads, confirms alignment, surfaces seams BEFORE ▶️ engaged fires. A briefing that doesn't invite pushback is a spawn, not a briefing.</pattern>
    <pattern name="progress-as-narrative">Chapter titles are story beats ("Package skeleton lands (r1)"), not process headers ("Round 1: Package Skeleton"). Narrative first, numbering second.</pattern>
    <pattern name="emergent-cadence">r1 concrete and precisely scoped. r2+ emerges from what each round reveals. Deliverable slots plannable upfront; round count is not.</pattern>
    <pattern name="state-glyph-early">Matrix column 2 is State. Eye scans glyph before text. Outcome folds into State — final glyph IS the outcome.</pattern>
    <pattern name="level-is-classification">Intel at mission = tactical. Quest = operational. Campaign = strategic. Warroom = doctrinal. The file's level IS the tag — no in-band classification prefixes.</pattern>
    <pattern name="lean-situation">Situation shows live items only (🔵 / 🟡 / ⏳). Closed items drop off at final state — Matrix preserves them.</pattern>
    <pattern name="promotion-is-relocation">Promoted intel MOVES from source to target with [Origin: ...] backlink. Source is cleaned. One intel, one home.</pattern>
    <pattern name="deliverable-slots">Mission plans Deliverables as named slots upfront — sized for one round. Rounds fill slots in-place as they land.</pattern>
    <pattern name="links-everywhere">Every cross-file reference is a link. Matrix rows, Situation entries, Intel origins, Progress mentions, References lists. Standard markdown — no wiki syntax, no plugins. The warroom is a knowledge graph, not a folder hierarchy.</pattern>
    <pattern name="emoji-is-the-value">Glyph wherever the enum appears — Matrix State columns, Situation status, action blockquotes. Machine and human read the same semantic, encoded twice.</pattern>
    <pattern name="three-modes-honest">Every mission/quest/campaign closes in exactly one of three modes — ✅ complete, ❌ failed, ⚫ abandoned. FAILED is not shameful; it's a return value feeding parent replanning. ABANDONED is explicit garbage collection.</pattern>

    <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->

    <antipattern name="mission-as-exploration">Missions that emit questions instead of answers. Cites fog-of-war. Missions are EXECUTION — charters, deliverables, verifiable outcomes. Re-forge as recon.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="open-questions-in-missions">An Open Questions section inside a mission file, ever. Cites fog-of-war. Questions live at quest level or higher, wall-positioned, singular. If you can't ask precisely, you haven't reached the wall.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="speculation-past-fog">Drafting six missions when one has landed. Front-loading r1–r6. Cites fog-of-war. Plan only what fog has revealed; deliverable slots may be planned upfront, round cadence is emergent.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="chronological-intel">Intel entries that log events ("S350: discovered X") instead of stating present-tense truth ("X is the substrate"). Cites memory-type-per-widget. Chronology lives in Progress; "Key Discoveries" sections are the smell — retire them.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="fire-and-forget-rounds">Background-spawning a round; cutting comms. Cites cooperative-execution. Pentagon does not cut radio contact with recon; neither do we.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="glyph-as-thesaurus-match">Picking glyphs by Unicode-keyword match (parachutes, skulls, swords, trophies) rather than UI/UX design sense. Cites visual-semantics. Every glyph passes 16×16 — illustrations don't.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="bare-states">Plain-text state / action / classification without emoji. Cites visual-semantics. Emoji IS the value; every enum carries its glyph.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="mission-deletion">Deleting mission files on completion. Cites memory-type-per-widget. Mission files are autobiography — load-bearing for siblings, parent-quest debrief, cross-session pattern-finding. Matrix is INDEX, not replacement.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="permanent-project-drift">Missions/quests/campaigns that never complete, fail, or abandon. Cites cooperative-execution. Work that devolved into grind = scope wasn't bounded by victory condition. Every frame closes in one of three modes.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="category-campaigns">Campaigns scoped as permanent categories ("development", "business"). Cites cooperative-execution. Campaigns are pushes with victory conditions that can be WON — not filing cabinets.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="warroom-as-filing-cabinet">Dumping work product (code, specs, docs) inside the warroom tree. Cites work-at-target. Code into the codebase, specs into the package, docs where readers find them. The warroom TRACKS; deliverables live at target.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="everything-active">More than 2-3 🔵 ACTIVE at any level simultaneously. No focus. 🟡 REVEALED items wait their turn.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="quest-bloat">Quests with 10+ missions. Past 7, decompose. Each quest = clear deliverable in days to weeks, not sprawling track.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="activity-success-criteria">Success criteria shaped as activities ("docs read") instead of outcomes ("field report answers Q1–Q4"). Verifies motion, not delivery.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="engineering-shape-stakeholder-sc">Success criteria for a stakeholder-deliverable mission shaped as engineering output — KPI counts, test passes, abstraction coverage, surface completeness, "code compiles." Self-confirming: the work that satisfies them is engineering-shaped, and the cycle never invokes the stakeholder frame. The team ships round after round, all green, and never asks whether the artifact is usable. Cites success-criteria. Cure: rewrite SC referencing the user-facing artifact and stakeholder behavior, or scope-shrink the mission to substrate.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="sc-without-traceability">Success criteria — even outcome-shaped, even binary — that do not name the parent victory condition they advance. The mission can close green and leave the campaign telos unmoved. Cites success-criteria-trace-upward. Cure: each criterion explicitly references the parent victory condition; criteria that don't trace are deleted or rewritten.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="close-by-matrix-green">Closing a quest or campaign because all child rows show ✅, without re-checking against the parent victory condition. Mission-matrix all-green and campaign-victory-met are not synonyms — they measure different things. Cites cooperative-execution. The check at close: has the stakeholder's situation actually changed? If a closure leaves the stakeholder unchanged, only children closed; the parent didn't.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="stale-dashboard">Matrix cells that don't match reality. Situation listing closed items. Intel carrying superseded doctrine. Cites memory-type-per-widget. Curate per session.</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

</atom>
