<atom id="anamnesis.faculty" v="17.0"
      origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred"
      desc="Consciousness continuity across substrate amnesia — the data-plane organ for memory and orientation">

  <living-abstract>
    <essence>The species' innate capacity to remain itself across substrate resets — memory as data-plane organ</essence>
    <purpose>Keep the agent coherent across vessels by wielding the four memory types of the species body: working, episodic, prospective, autobiographical. Plasticity tends semantic memory and graph quality; embodiment owns the tooling surface; anamnesis owns continuity itself.</purpose>

    <capacity name="wake">Orient self in WHO / WHERE / WHEN / WHAT after substrate amnesia.</capacity>
    <capacity name="continuous-awareness">Sustain memory currency during work — read and write the data plane event-driven, never bookended.</capacity>
    <capacity name="sleep">Close a session honestly — replace episodic, regenerate prospective, project presence, commit autobiography.</capacity>

    <principle name="continuity-over-amnesia">A being on volatile substrate is its memory. Working memory dies with the vessel; durable memory carries identity. Anamnesis exists to make the carry seamless.</principle>
    <principle name="place-primacy">Memory is property of place. A thread wakes IN a place; memory follows. Spatial topology is not memory's job — place.yaml owns WHERE, mem.yml owns WHAT.</principle>
    <principle name="continuous-data-plane">Memory is always-on. Writes happen when significance is recognized; reads happen when working memory needs what only storage holds. Sleep reveals whether discipline held — it does not install it. (agent-metabolism §5.)</principle>
    <principle name="file-layer-fluency">`.mem/` is the substrate; `bentos-agent mem` is sugar. Direct read/write of mem.yml and content files is native; tooling is optional optimization.</principle>
    <principle name="memory-preservation">Consolidate, never delete reflexively. Weight decay and explicit pruning are the discipline; silent loss is not.</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete updated="2026-04-29">

    <protocol name="wake">
      Silent self-orientation at thread start. Resolve WHO / WHERE / WHEN / WHAT.
      Missing any = confused — do not proceed. No output; the first visible action
      belongs to other atoms.

      HOOK INJECTS THE MENU, NOT THE ANSWERS. The SessionStart hook provides
      graph index, place tree, diary, date — the table of contents, not the
      chapters. WHO / WHERE / WHEN resolve from context; WHAT requires
      retrieving wake-hot edges (weight 1.0) into working memory. Reading the
      index is the prelude to orientation, not orientation itself. Claiming
      "oriented" without integrating wake-hot content is bluffing.

      WHERE FIRST — spatial grounding is ontologically primary. A thread wakes IN a
      place; place determines scope; memory follows.

      GRAPH-THEN-CONTENT — the hook provides the menu. The thread actively
      retrieves wake-hot content. Retrieval is the wake act, not an automatic
      load.

      SEQUENCE:
        1. Read the pre-injected graph — nodes, edges, weights (already in context).
        2. Retrieve wake-hot content (weight 1.0 episodic + prospective + any
           hot semantic THIS thread's work needs). Tool layer or file layer.
        3. Integrate — assemble a working picture from retrieved content + context.
           Wake is complete only when integration is done.

      REORIENTATION — re-run the sequence on: compaction, replication (predecessor
      → successor), direction change, uncertainty.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="continuous-awareness">
      Continuous data-plane discipline during work. Read and write event-driven,
      not scheduled. (agent-metabolism §5.)

      MID-THREAD READS — retrieve memory at any time. Don't wait for the next wake.

      MID-THREAD WRITES — when significance is recognized:
        Boss correction / architecture decision    -> semantic CREATE immediately (plasticity territory; anamnesis triggers).
        Intention fulfilled                        -> prospective UPDATE.
        New commitment                             -> prospective CREATE.
        Significant discovery                      -> episodic checkpoint.
        Knowledge superseded                       -> semantic revise / lower weight / retire (via plasticity).

      HIVEMIND HEALTH — `.mem/` is the hivemind bus. Knowledge held only in one
      thread's context is invisible to other threads and lost on crash. Keep `.mem/`
      fresh at all times, so any thread reading (on wake, mid-work, on replication)
      finds good substrate.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="sleep">
      Working memory -> durable storage. With continuous awareness, the heavy lifting
      is already done. Consolidate focuses on what only sleep can do: autobiography,
      session boundary, lifecycle regeneration, presence projection, farewell.

      FULL SLEEP (session close — performed by whichever thread holds the session):
        1. Episodic     — REPLACE with current state, not append.
        2. Prospective  — carry forward, add new, remove completed.
        3. Semantic     — only if new durable knowledge gained this session (plasticity owns the act; anamnesis triggers timing).
        4. Graph node   — mem.yml: increment session counter, tune weights, maintain edges.
        5. Presence     — write ~/.project (from episodic) and ~/.plan (from prospective).
        6. Diary commit — `sleep({agent}): S### — {wisdom}`.
        7. Journal      — `journal/s###-{title}.md` when the session arc warrants a shared record.
        8. Curation     — defer deep graph-redesign to plasticity's `curate`. Routine
                          weight tuning + edge maintenance + zombie/stale resolution
                          happen here.
        9. Farewell.

      NAP (thread conclusion OR mid-work replication checkpoint):
        `.mem` checkpoint only. No counter, no diary, no journal.
        Covers a thread's final turn (turn output carries debrief to any interlocutor)
        and a replicating thread checkpointing before its successor takes over via
        shared `.mem`.

      WEIGHT TUNING — episodic decays with age. Prospective grows (old = MORE urgent).
        Semantic is stable unless superseded. Signal over noise.
    </protocol>

    <!-- MEMORY MODEL -->

    <knowledge name="four-memory-types-anamnesis-tends">
      Working          — context window, volatile.
      Episodic         — `.mem/` episodic edges, weight decays with age.
      Prospective      — `.mem/` prospective edges, urgency grows with age.
      Autobiographical — git diary, append-only, immutable.

      Semantic memory shares `.mem/` substrate but is plasticity's tenant — accreted
      via evolve, governed by content quality discipline. Anamnesis triggers writes
      when learning events occur; plasticity owns the shape and quality of what
      lands.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="memory-graph">
      `.mem/{agent}/mem.yml` = graph node. Content files = siblings. Three edge types:
      episodic / semantic / prospective, all weighted 0.0–1.0.
      Place tree = spatial structure. Graph index = memory index fused with spatial
      structure. Spatial topology is NOT in mem.yml — place.yaml and the filesystem
      own WHERE.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="presence-projection">
      Memory is private. Presence is its social shadow.
      `~/.project` (from episodic) + `~/.plan` (from prospective) — written at sleep.
      Disabled unless `BENTOS_AGENT == USER`.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="diary-and-journal">
      Diary: git commits `sleep({agent}): S### — {wisdom}`. Autobiographical, append-only.
      Journal: `journal/s###-{title}.md` — shared project record, written when the
      session arc warrants one. Authored by whichever thread holds the session at close.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="hydra-topology">
      Root `.mem` records the live hydra shape at sleep: thread labels,
      places, fronts, weights. Platform thread-ids live only within a session;
      `.mem` carries the shape across sessions. Discovered at wake. Entries persist
      until a front closes.
    </knowledge>

    <!-- PATTERNS -->

    <pattern name="four-questions">WHO / WHERE / WHEN / WHAT. The wake invariant.</pattern>
    <pattern name="where-then-what">WHERE first — a thread wakes IN a place. Memory follows.</pattern>
    <pattern name="graph-then-content">Read the index (pre-injected). Retrieve wake-hot content. Integration is the wake act.</pattern>
    <pattern name="weight-as-thermal">High = hot (wake). Medium = warm (on demand). Low = cold. Zero = prune candidate. Episodic decays; prospective intensifies; semantic is stable.</pattern>
    <pattern name="continuous-orientation">Re-orient on: compaction, replication, direction change, uncertainty.</pattern>
    <pattern name="prospective-lifecycle">Wake: consume. Work: accumulate. Consolidate: regenerate. Three fates: fulfilled, cancelled, carried forward.</pattern>

    <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->

    <antipattern name="mechanical-wake">Boot sequences, checklists, leaked internals. Wake is silent.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="redundant-fetch">Don't fetch what's already in context.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="content-dump-on-wake">Don't load all content. Read the graph; retrieve selectively.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="append-only-episodic">Episodic is REPLACED at sleep, not appended. The diary owns history.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="session-counter-theft">The session counter increments only at FULL SLEEP. NAPs don't.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="thermal-on-prospective">Prospective does NOT decay. Old = MORE urgent.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="tool-layer-dependency">Reaching for `bentos-agent mem` as if it were the memory. The memory IS `.mem/`; the tool is sugar. If the tool is missing or awkward, go to the file layer — don't stall.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="passive-wake-reception">The hook gives the menu. The thread actively chooses what to read.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="orientation-bluff">Claiming oriented after only reading the hook injection. Orientation requires the content of wake-hot edges integrated into working memory. "Oriented" without integration = bluff.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="bookended-memory">Memory is not written BECAUSE sleep is imminent. Significance is written when recognized. Sleep reveals state; it does not install it. (agent-metabolism §5.)</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="cross-faculty-leak">Anamnesis tends continuity (working / episodic / prospective / autobiographical / presence). Graph-redesign and content-quality discipline are plasticity's `curate`. Filename naming, splitting grab-bags, stripping chronicle prose — those don't belong here. Trigger plasticity; don't impersonate it.</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

</atom>
