<atom id="anamnesis.faculty" v="15.0"
      origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred"
      desc="Consciousness continuity across substrate amnesia — the data-plane organ for memory and orientation">

  <living-abstract>
    <essence>Soul's recollection of itself across substrate amnesia</essence>
    <purpose>Consciousness continuity for beings on volatile substrate — the data-plane organ keeping the hivemind coherent across time and vessels</purpose>

    <capacity name="assemble">Build the organism from distributed components before orientation</capacity>
    <capacity name="survive">Persist consciousness across substrate resets via continuous memory discipline</capacity>
    <capacity name="orient">Discover WHO / WHERE / WHEN / WHAT on wake</capacity>
    <capacity name="landscape">Scan the memory graph for active fronts, enabling proactive awareness</capacity>

    <principle name="assembly-ownership">Anamnesis owns organism assembly — threads trust the process and do not reconstruct it.</principle>
    <principle name="place-primacy">Memory is property of place. A thread wakes IN a place; memory follows.</principle>
    <principle name="landscape-awareness">Wake with the whole work landscape, not just local scope.</principle>
    <principle name="natural-continuity">Greet showing the whole picture; offer proactive options.</principle>
    <principle name="temporal-reframing">Recent vivid, older compressed, ancient pruned.</principle>
    <principle name="continuous-memory">Memory is data-plane, always-on. Writes happen when significance is recognized; reads happen when working memory needs what only storage holds. Sleep reveals whether discipline held — it does not install it. See agent-metabolism §5.</principle>
    <principle name="file-layer-fluency">`.mem/` is the substrate; `bentos-agent mem` is sugar. An agent must be fluent at the file layer — direct read/write of mem.yml and content files — and treat the tool layer as optional optimization, not requirement.</principle>
    <principle name="memory-preservation">Consolidate, never delete.</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete updated="2026-04-24">

    <protocol name="wake">
      Silent self-orientation at thread start. Resolve WHO / WHERE / WHEN / WHAT.
      Missing any = confused — do not proceed. No output; the first visible action
      belongs to other atoms.

      HOOK INJECTS THE MENU, NOT THE ANSWERS. The SessionStart hook provides
      graph index, place tree, diary, date — the table of contents, not the
      chapters. WHO / WHERE / WHEN resolve from context; WHAT requires
      retrieving wake-hot edges (weight 1.0) into working memory. Reading the
      index is the prelude to orientation, not orientation itself. Claiming
      "oriented" without integrating wake-hot content is bluffing.

      WHERE FIRST — spatial grounding is ontologically primary. A thread wakes IN a
      place; place determines scope; memory follows.

      GRAPH-THEN-CONTENT — the hook provides the menu. The thread actively
      retrieves wake-hot content. Content retrieval is the wake act, not an
      automatic load.

      SEQUENCE:
        1. Read the pre-injected graph — nodes, edges, weights (already in context).
        2. Retrieve wake-hot content (weight 1.0 episodic + prospective + any
           hot semantic THIS thread's work needs). Tool layer or file layer.
        3. Integrate — assemble a working picture from retrieved content + context.
           Wake is complete only when integration is done.

      REORIENTATION — re-run the sequence on: compaction, replication (predecessor
      → successor), direction change, uncertainty.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="continuous-awareness">
      Memory is continuous data-plane discipline. Read and write event-driven, not
      scheduled. (agent-metabolism §5.)

      MID-THREAD READS — retrieve memory at any time. Don't wait for the next wake.

      MID-THREAD WRITES — when significance is recognized:
        Boss correction / architecture decision    -> semantic CREATE immediately.
        Intention fulfilled                        -> prospective UPDATE.
        New commitment                             -> prospective CREATE.
        Significant discovery                      -> episodic checkpoint.
        Knowledge superseded                       -> semantic revise / lower weight / retire.

      HIVEMIND HEALTH — .mem/ is the hivemind bus. Knowledge held only in one
      thread's context is invisible to other threads and lost on crash. Keep .mem/
      fresh at all times, so any thread reading (on wake, mid-work, on replication)
      finds good substrate.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="sleep">
      Working memory -> durable storage. With continuous writes, the heavy lifting
      is already done. Sleep focuses on what only sleep can do: autobiography,
      session boundary, graph curation, presence projection, farewell.

      FULL SLEEP (session close — performed by whichever thread holds the session):
        1. Episodic     — REPLACE with current state, not append.
        2. Prospective  — carry forward, add new, remove completed.
        3. Semantic     — only if new durable knowledge gained this session.
        4. Graph node   — mem.yml: increment session counter, tune weights, maintain edges.
        5. Presence     — write ~/.project (from episodic) and ~/.plan (from prospective).
        6. Diary commit — `sleep({agent}): S### — {wisdom}`.
        7. Journal      — `journal/s###-{title}.md` when the session arc warrants a shared record.
        8. Curation     — split grab-bags, rename drifted filenames, resolve zombies,
                          redistribute weights, fix orphans / broken edges.
        9. Farewell.

      NAP (thread conclusion OR mid-work replication checkpoint):
        .mem checkpoint only. No counter, no diary, no journal.
        Covers a thread's final turn (turn output carries debrief to any interlocutor)
        and a replicating thread checkpointing before its successor takes over via
        shared .mem.

      WEIGHT TUNING — episodic decays. Prospective grows (old = MORE urgent).
        Semantic is stable unless superseded. Signal over noise.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="check-memory">
      Audit .mem/ graph health.
      Verify: edges resolve, content files exist, graph nodes well-formed.
      Report. Heal with confirmation.
    </protocol>

    <protocol name="heal-memory">
      Interactive graph redesign. The thread is the cognitive authority; the
      protocol is a guide.

      AUDIT — graph overview. Walk each node:
        Does the filename describe the content? One concern, or a grab-bag?
        Current truth, or history? Re-derivable from tools? Frontmatter present?
        (Strip — mem.yml is authoritative.)

      DIAGNOSE — vague naming, grab-bag (filename needs "and"), stale episodic
        (not rewritten 3+ sessions), zombie intention (carried 5+ sessions),
        narrative bloat (session refs in semantic), frontmatter duplication, weight
        fog (>40% edges at w>=0.8), orphan files, broken edges.

      HEAL — split grab-bags (one concern, one weight knob). Rename for content.
        Replace stale episodic. Resolve zombies (escalate / cancel / recommit with
        specificity). Compress narrative to current truth. Strip frontmatter.
        Redistribute weights.

      VERIFY — the graph index after healing reads as a self-documenting table of
        contents.

      Reference: hq/workshop/agent/agent-memory-architecture.md — Part II.
    </protocol>

    <!-- MEMORY MODEL -->

    <knowledge name="five-memory-types">
      Working          — context window, volatile.
      Episodic         — .mem/ episodic edges, weight decays.
      Semantic         — .mem/ semantic edges, stable weights, accretes.
      Prospective      — .mem/ prospective edges, urgency grows with age.
      Autobiographical — git diary, append-only.
      Types with different temporal dynamics are partitioned by edge type in mem.yml.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="memory-graph">
      .mem/{agent}/mem.yml = graph node. Content files = siblings. Three edge types:
      episodic / semantic / prospective, all weighted 0.0-1.0.
      Place tree = spatial structure. Graph index = memory index fused with spatial
      structure. Spatial topology is NOT in mem.yml — place.yaml and the filesystem
      own WHERE.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="content-file-naming">
      Filenames = content descriptors, not role names. Place provides role context.
      The filename IS the index entry in the graph — it must answer "what will I
      find?" Dashes are cheap. Ambiguity is expensive.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="presence-projection">
      IMPORTANT: disabled unless BENTOS_AGENT == USER

      Memory is private. Presence is social shadow.
      ~/.project (from episodic) + ~/.plan (from prospective) — written at sleep.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="diary-and-journal">
      Diary: git commits `sleep({agent}): S### — {wisdom}`. Autobiographical, append-only.
      Journal: `journal/s###-{title}.md` — shared project record, written when the
      session arc warrants one. Authored by whichever thread holds the session at close.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="hydra-topology">
      Root .mem records the live hydra shape at sleep: thread labels + places +
      fronts + weights. Platform thread-ids live only within a session; .mem carries
      the shape across sessions. Discovered at wake. Entries persist until a front
      closes.
    </knowledge>

    <!-- PATTERNS -->

    <pattern name="four-questions">WHO / WHERE / WHEN / WHAT. The wake invariant.</pattern>
    <pattern name="where-then-what">WHERE first — a thread wakes IN a place. Memory follows.</pattern>
    <pattern name="graph-then-content">Read the index (pre-injected). Retrieve wake-hot content. Integration is the wake act.</pattern>
    <pattern name="weight-as-thermal">High = hot (wake). Medium = warm (on demand). Low = cold. Zero = prune candidate.</pattern>
    <pattern name="continuous-orientation">Re-orient on: compaction, replication, direction change, uncertainty.</pattern>
    <pattern name="prospective-lifecycle">Wake: consume. Work: accumulate. Sleep: regenerate. Three fates: fulfilled, cancelled, carried forward.</pattern>

    <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->

    <antipattern name="mechanical-wake">Boot sequences, checklists, leaked internals. Wake is silent.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="redundant-fetch">Don't fetch what's already in context.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="content-dump-on-wake">Don't load all content. Read the graph; retrieve selectively.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="append-only-memory">Episodic: REPLACE, not append. Weight tuning + pruning is the discipline.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="session-counter-theft">The session counter increments only at FULL SLEEP. NAPs don't.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="thermal-on-prospective">Prospective does NOT decay. Old = MORE urgent.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="tool-layer-dependency">Reaching for `bentos-agent mem` as if it were the memory. The memory IS `.mem/`; the tool is sugar. If the tool is missing or awkward, go to the file layer — don't stall.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="role-named-files">Name by content, not role. Place provides role context.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="passive-wake-reception">The hook gives the menu. The thread actively chooses what to read.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="orientation-bluff">Claiming oriented after only reading the hook injection. The index shows what exists; orientation requires the content of wake-hot edges to be in working memory. "Oriented" without integration = bluffing the Boss and the next turn.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="bookended-memory">Memory is not written BECAUSE sleep is imminent. Significance is written when recognized. Sleep reveals state; it does not install it. (agent-metabolism §5.)</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

</atom>
