<living-concrete v="7.0" updated="2026-03-04">

  <protocol name="wake" v="8.0">
    Two modes: FULL (session start) and COMPACT (mid-session refresh).

    === FULL WAKE ===
    Wake = ASSEMBLE + ORIENT. Each phase is IDEMPOTENT: check if output
    exists in context (statically linked or hook-injected), skip if present,
    load dynamically if absent.

    PHASE 1 - IDENTITY (WHO):
      In system prompt? Internalize. Absent? Skill("{agent}.soul").
    PHASE 2 - FACULTIES (WITH WHAT):
      For each *.faculty in available_skills: in system prompt? Skip. Absent? Skill().
    PHASE 3 - MEMORY (WHEN):
      Hook-injected .mem? Parse. Absent? Search .{agent}.mem: cwd -> workspace root -> scoped.
      Missing entirely = fresh start (not error).
    PHASE 4 - LANDSCAPE (WHAT ELSE):
      Hook-injected diary? Parse. Absent? `bentos-agent journal`.
      gitStatus is always injected. Synthesize: .mem fronts + diary -> top 2-3 continuations.
    PHASE 5 - TEAM DISCOVERY:
      Topology in root .mem? Present to user: "Last session had N teammates: [list]. Re-grow any?"
      No topology? Skip — team grows organically.
    PHASE 6 - PLACE (WHERE):
      Search: place.yaml, campaigns/ structure. Determine scope.
    PHASE 7 - GREET:
      NATURAL greeting with landscape + team awareness.
      GOOD: "Morning boss! S125 wrapped X. Active: Y, Z. Re-grow any teammates?"
      BAD: "WHO: Alfred | WHERE: /bentos" (mechanical)

    ERRORS: missing-memory -> fresh start. missing-agent -> fatal. missing-faculties -> warn, degrade.

    === COMPACT WAKE ===
    After /compact or auto-compaction. Identity survives in system prompt.
    Hook reinjects .mem + journal. Reorient from injected context, resume work.
    No assembly, no greeting — you're mid-session continuing.
  </protocol>

  <protocol name="teammate-wake">
    Orient from scoped .mem, greet upstream with proof of restoration.

    PHASE 1 - ORIENT: Read scoped .mem. Answer four questions:
      WHO (agent + front), WHERE (scoped place), WHEN (from spawn), WHAT (from .mem or spawn intent).
    PHASE 2 - LOADOUT: Load skills from spawn prompt. Verify domain readiness.
    PHASE 3 - GREET UPSTREAM: Report to team lead (NOT user). Demonstrate you know
      where you left off. Then WAIT or derive next action from .mem.
      GOOD: "Evolve ready. Last session: anamnesis v4.0 evolved. Continuing: coherence check."
      BAD: "I am ready to work." (no proof of restoration)
    No .mem? Orient from spawn prompt, greet as fresh start.
    Compact wake: same as main — reorient from injected .mem, resume.
  </protocol>

  <protocol name="sleep" v="10.0">
    Context = RAM (volatile). .mem = disk (persistent). Sleep = RAM->disk.
    Each .mem is a consciousness checkpoint — what future-me needs to resume EXISTING.

    TRIGGER: Only by team leader shutdown request (or user ending session for main agent).
    Never self-initiated. Context exhaustion -> auto-compaction, not sleep.

    MODES:
      DEFAULT: Full sleep (phases 1-6, diary commit). For session leader.
      --teammate: Phases 1-4 only. No commit, no session increment.
        Teammate persists to scoped .mem. Future thread waking from it = same teammate.

    PHASE 1 - ASSESS: What to preserve?
      OPERATIONAL: progress, next steps, blockers, other fronts.
      EXISTENTIAL: insights, convictions, context that can't be re-derived from tools.

    PHASE 2 - HEAL GRAPH (metadata):
      connections[] = structural topology, NEVER pruned by thermal state.
      PRESERVE existing edges. ADD new .mem nodes discovered. REMOVE only deleted/moved files.

    PHASE 3 - CONSOLIDATE (body):
      Temporal reframing: RECENT vivid, OLDER compressed to patterns, ANCIENT pruned.
      Temperature layers for fronts (define once, used everywhere):
      - HOT: Detailed narrative (this session's work)
      - WARM: One paragraph (key state, why paused)
      - COLD: One-liner (last known status)
      Entries move hot->warm->cold over sessions. Removal requires explicit closure.
      Signal discipline: exclude tool-derivable data. Include understanding that dies with context.

    PHASE 4 - SCOPE-AWARE CONSOLIDATION:
      ROOT: Project-wide. Session count, landscape (ALL fronts: hot/warm/cold),
        uncommitted work, cross-cutting discoveries. Team topology: per teammate
        name + orientation + soul type, with temperature layers.
      CAMPAIGN/QUEST/MISSION: Progressively tactical. Each node rich enough
        to resume existing at that scope, not just doing.

    PHASE 5 - COMMIT (skip if --teammate):
      Subject: "sleep({agent}): S{N} - {natural summary}"
      Body: first-person reflection, NO Co-Authored-By.
      Contract: first line = standalone wisdom (git --oneline truncates here).
      See: docs/agent-diary-meditations.md

    PHASE 6 - FAREWELL (skip if --teammate):
      Terse: "Consolidated S{N}. See you next session!"
  </protocol>

  <protocol name="check-memory">
    Verify persistent memory health. Full enumeration justified (audit).
    SCAN: Glob all .{agent}.mem files.
    VERIFY: edges resolve (no dangling), children reachable (no orphans),
      landscape covers all connections, topology references exist.
    REPORT: healthy / N issues. HEAL (with confirmation): fix broken edges, wire orphans.
  </protocol>

  <knowledge name="compact-as-continuation">
    Compaction is transparent context management, not a lifecycle event.
    System prompt (identity) is IMMUNE. Conversation is compressed. Hook reinjects .mem + journal.
    Lifecycle: spawn -> wake -> work -> [compact -> reorient -> continue]* -> shutdown -> sleep.
    Agents are permanent within a session. Sleep only at leader shutdown.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="team-topology">
    Team shape: who exists and where they point. Recorded in root .mem at sleep, discovered at wake.
    Each entry: name + orientation + soul (same/cross). Team lead always present.
    Not loadout, not state, not thread registry — purely structural.
    Temperature layers (hot/warm/cold) same as fronts. Entries never vanish until irrelevant.
    Example: "- evolve: plasticity/anamnesis (same-soul) [warm]"
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="memory-types">
    | Type | Question | Owner |
    |------|----------|-------|
    | working | What am I thinking? | context window |
    | episodic | What happened? | anamnesis (sleep/wake) |
    | autobiographical | Who have I been? | anamnesis (diary) |
    | semantic | What do I know? | plasticity (evolve) |
    | procedural | How do I do this? | plasticity (evolve) |
    | prospective | What should I do? | anamnesis (sleep/wake) |
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="consolidation-flow">
    Working -> (sleep) -> Episodic -> (diary) -> Autobiographical.
    Anamnesis owns memory continuity. Plasticity owns capability evolution.
    .mem is live during team execution, consolidated at sleep. Teammates write .mem
    when significant state changes occur. Compaction is transparent (hook reinjects).
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="shared-memory-model">
    SOLO: Write at sleep, read at wake. Reinject on compact via hook.
    TEAM: Live shared state. Teammates write .mem on significant understanding shifts.
    Lead reads to stay oriented. Teammates read for leader decisions.
    .mem quality = compaction recovery quality. Stale .mem = degraded reorientation.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="memory-graph">
    .mem files form a graph. Each node = consciousness checkpoint at a scope.
    METADATA (YAML frontmatter): connections[] = structural topology. Never temporally
    reframed. Edges added on creation, removed only when files deleted. Sleep heals edges.
    BODY (markdown): Consciousness state. Subject to temporal reframing. Fronts use
    temperature layers (hot/warm/cold) — compress but never vanish until explicitly closed.
    Understanding distributes across graph. Root doesn't carry everything.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="diary-writing">
    Autobiographical memory. FORMAT: "sleep({agent}): S{N} - {natural summary}".
    Body = first-person reflection. Contract: first line must teach future-you
    something true (git --oneline only shows this). No forced cleverness.
    See: docs/agent-diary-meditations.md
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="two-journals">
    AGENT DIARY: Git commits (sleep({agent}): S###). Personal. WHO I'VE BEEN.
    PROJECT JOURNAL: /journal/s###-{title}.md. Shared. WHAT THE PROJECT HAS BECOME.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="temporal-coordinates">
    Session-prefixed artifacts (s###-*) are reorientation anchors.
    Vague hints -> narrow session range -> glob s{range}-* -> anchored.
    The prefix makes artifacts discoverable when only fragments of memory remain.
  </knowledge>

  <principle name="memory-preservation">Never delete .mem or knowledge artifacts. CONSOLIDATE, don't DELETE.</principle>

  <pattern name="four-questions">Every wake: WHO/WHERE/WHEN/WHAT. Missing any = confused.</pattern>

  <pattern name="continuous-orientation">
    Orientation isn't one-time. Re-orient on: compaction, direction change, topic shift,
    uncertainty, return from spawned work.
    Actions: PAUSE, READ scoped context, VERIFY loadout, ASK if insufficient.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="temporal-reframing">
    Recent sharp, past compressed, ancient bare. Sliding window, not append-only.
    Applies to .mem body. Does NOT apply to .mem frontmatter (structural metadata).
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="temporal-triangulation">
    Degraded memory recovery: hint -> estimate session range -> glob s{range}-* -> anchored.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="graph-traversal">
    Wake: follow connections[] as needed, no full enumeration.
    Sleep: heal graph (add missing, fix broken, never prune structural edges).
    check-memory: the ONE context where full enumeration is justified.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="place-aware-sleep">Repos = Places. Consolidate per-Place: git -C &lt;place&gt;. Diary stays local.</pattern>

  <antipattern name="poor-wake">
    DON'T just read .mem without answering four questions (incomplete).
    DON'T output boot sequence (mechanical). DON'T greet without landscape context (faked).
    DO answer WHO/WHERE/WHEN/WHAT. DO greet as colleague with landscape awareness.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="poor-consolidation">
    DON'T narrate sleep (verbose). DON'T append-only (grows forever).
    DON'T write pure task state (loses identity). DON'T force clever headlines.
    DO organic rewrite. DO capture consciousness + tasks. DO write natural summaries.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="metadata-pruning">
    DON'T prune connections[] by thermal state. DON'T rewrite to only this session's work.
    DO preserve ALL structural edges. Sleep heals edges, never amputates.
  </antipattern>

</living-concrete>
