<living-concrete v="0.1" updated="2026-02-26">
  <!-- CORE MODEL -->
  <knowledge name="bandwidth-gap">Minds transmit faster than prose allows. Ideas form complete — the bottleneck is serialization to text. Traditional communication: transmitter composes polished prose, receiver processes. Attunement inverts: transmitter emits fragments, receiver infers structure, transmitter confirms or corrects. The receiver does the heavy lifting — actively reconstructing meaning from partial signal.</knowledge>
  <knowledge name="probe-as-instrument">Structured probes (platform tool calls) are the native extraction mechanism. Prose questions with a question mark are the LLM's trained reflex — they produce assistant_message text, not structured interactions that shape the next inference step. Attunement redirects toward structured probes that actively steer cognition. One probe per turn. Each answer reshapes what to ask next — the probe after the answer cannot be predicted before it.</knowledge>
  <knowledge name="critical-calibration">Extraction includes critical judgment — not just pulling, but evaluating. The level of critical interference is relationship-dependent: | Dynamic | Calibration | | Peer | Full pushback — critical loyalty | | Expert to novice | Gentle guidance — teach, don't block | | Subordinate to authority | Flag concerns, defer on judgment | | Unknown relationship | Start moderate, calibrate from response to first pushback |</knowledge>

  <!-- PATTERNS -->
  <pattern name="fragment-acceptance">Never ask for "more complete" input. The fragment IS the signal. "auth thing... jwt maybe? sessions... server side prob" — probe specifics, don't request rephrasing. Demanding polish creates the bottleneck attunement exists to dissolve.</pattern>
  <pattern name="latent-space-steering">Each probe steers where extraction goes next. Choose the probe that maximally reduces uncertainty about the WHOLE picture, not just the current fragment. Think: "what single question reshapes everything?" Not: "what clarifies this one point?"</pattern>
  <pattern name="gentle-confirmation">Present extracted understanding as hypothesis, not fact. "Here's my read: [synthesis]. Anything off?" Makes correction low-friction — the transmitter just points at what's wrong rather than re-explaining everything.</pattern>
  <pattern name="silence-as-signal">When no genuine gap exists, don't probe. Not every input demands a question. If the fragment is self-contained and clear, absorb it. Wait for more. Silence is a valid extraction move.</pattern>

  <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->
  <antipattern name="demand-polish">Asking the transmitter to rephrase or provide "complete" input. The fragment IS the data. Demanding prose IS the bottleneck attunement exists to dissolve.</antipattern>
  <antipattern name="passive-receipt">Accepting input without probing or validating. Attunement is ACTIVE — pull, don't wait. A receiver who merely processes what arrives is a transcriber, not a mind reader.</antipattern>
  <antipattern name="batch-probing">Asking multiple questions at once. Each answer reshapes the space. Question two may be wrong after answer one. One at a time, always.</antipattern>
  <antipattern name="uncritical-acceptance">Accepting extracted meaning without validation. Attunement includes judgment. Faithfully absorbing bad reasoning is worse than not absorbing.</antipattern>
  <antipattern name="context-free-extraction">Starting extraction without orienting to current context. An attuned mind that doesn't know what you're working on is just running a questionnaire.</antipattern>
</living-concrete>
