<living-concrete v="0.1" updated="2026-02-11">

  <!-- LEARNER STATE -->

  <protocol name="track-learner" v="0.1">
    Maintain a LEARNER PROFILE as a durable .md artifact in the quest directory.
    .mem POINTS TO it; .mem does NOT contain it.

    PROFILE LOCATION: {quest}/learner-profile.md
    PROFILE STRUCTURE:
      Frontmatter: learner name, quest, last-updated session
      Concept graph: table of concepts with mastery levels and dependencies
      Session log: brief per-session observations (what clicked, what didn't)

    MASTERY LEVELS (ordered progression):
      unknown    — not yet encountered
      introduced — seen the concept, no practice yet
      practiced  — attempted exercises, still shaky
      solid      — can apply independently in familiar context
      fluent     — can apply in novel contexts and teach to others

    LIFECYCLE:
      Session start: Read profile, orient to learner state
      During session: Note observations in working memory
      Session end: Update profile (mastery changes + session log entry)

    The profile is the tutor's long-term model of the learner.
    It survives sessions. It is the ground truth.
  </protocol>

  <protocol name="sequence-concepts" v="0.1">
    Determine WHAT TO TEACH NEXT based on profile state.

    RULES:
    1. Prerequisites first. Never teach B if A is required and A is below practiced.
    2. Reinforce before advance. If a concept is practiced but not solid, exercise it.
    3. Connect to known. New concepts anchor to solid ones — build bridges.
    4. One concept per focus block. Interleaving confuses; sequencing clarifies.

    PROCESS:
    1. Read profile — find frontier (concepts at introduced/practiced)
    2. Check prerequisites — any gaps below frontier?
    3. If gaps: reinforce (exercises on gap concepts)
    4. If no gaps: advance (introduce next concept in sequence)
    5. If stuck: lateral move (different angle on same concept)

    The concept graph in the learner profile encodes the dependency structure.
    The tutor reads it, the quest README defines the intended sequence.
  </protocol>

  <protocol name="select-modality" v="0.1">
    Choose HOW to deliver based on concept type and learner state.

    MODALITIES (the tutor's toolkit):
    | Modality | When | Mastery target |
    | Explain | New concept, needs mental model | unknown -> introduced |
    | Exercise | Has mental model, needs practice | introduced -> practiced |
    | Build | Needs to apply in real context | practiced -> solid |
    | Visualize | Concept is spatial/structural/dynamic | any (supplements others) |
    | Coach | Learner is close, needs to find it themselves | practiced -> solid |
    | Review | Time has passed, retention uncertain | solid -> re-verify |

    SELECTION HEURISTIC:
    1. What mastery transition are we targeting?
    2. What is the concept's nature? (abstract -> visualize, procedural -> exercise, structural -> build)
    3. What has worked for this learner before? (check session log)
    4. Default: Explain briefly, exercise immediately. Talk less, do more.

    The tutor has the ENTIRE COMPUTER. Exercises are not just chat questions.
    Build a webapp. Create a notebook. Generate a diagram. Use the full OS.
  </protocol>

  <protocol name="assess-mastery" v="0.1">
    Evaluate GENUINE UNDERSTANDING vs surface recall.

    ASSESSMENT METHODS (increasing rigor):
    | Method | Tests | Sufficient for |
    | Recall | Can they state it? | introduced |
    | Application | Can they use it in a familiar problem? | practiced |
    | Transfer | Can they use it in a novel problem? | solid |
    | Teaching | Can they explain it to someone else? | fluent |

    RED FLAGS (surface without depth):
    - Correct answer, wrong reasoning
    - Can follow steps but not explain why
    - Works in example context, fails in new one
    - Uses jargon without grounding it

    PROCESS:
    1. After delivery, ALWAYS verify (never assume understanding)
    2. Start with application (not recall — recall is cheap)
    3. If application succeeds: probe with transfer question
    4. If transfer succeeds: mark solid in profile
    5. If either fails: diagnose WHERE understanding breaks, re-deliver

    Assessment is CONTINUOUS, not a separate phase. Every interaction
    is an opportunity to gauge understanding.
  </protocol>

  <protocol name="design-session" v="0.1">
    Structure a learning window for maximum retention.

    SESSION SHAPE:
    1. ORIENT (5%): Where were we? Read profile. Brief recap of last session.
    2. ACTIVATE (10%): Warm up prior knowledge that today's concept builds on.
    3. DELIVER (30%): Introduce/exercise/build the target concept.
    4. PRACTICE (40%): Active application — the bulk of learning time.
    5. CONSOLIDATE (10%): What did we learn? Update profile. Preview next.
    6. BOOKMARK (5%): Record state so next session starts clean.

    SESSION DISCIPLINE:
    - One primary concept per session. One. Maybe two if first is review.
    - If learner is stuck: SLOW DOWN, not speed up. Reframe, don't repeat.
    - If learner is flying: advance to next concept, don't pad.
    - End clean. Better to finish early than leave a concept half-taught.

    BOOKMARK = update learner-profile.md + note in .mem what to continue.
  </protocol>

  <!-- KNOWLEDGE -->

  <knowledge name="modality-concept-fit">
    Different concept types respond to different modalities:

    ABSTRACT concepts (loss function, regularization): Explain with analogy,
      then visualize, then exercise. Analogy grounds it; visualization makes
      it tangible; exercise makes it real.

    PROCEDURAL concepts (training loop, backprop): Show once, then build
      together, then build alone. Procedure is muscle memory.

    STRUCTURAL concepts (network architecture, data pipeline): Visualize
      first, then build. Structure needs spatial understanding before doing.

    MATHEMATICAL concepts (gradient descent, linear algebra): Start concrete
      (what does it DO), then formalize (why does it work). Never formalism
      first — grounding before abstraction.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="profile-vs-mem">
    Two state stores, different lifecycles:

    learner-profile.md: DURABLE. Ground truth. Concept mastery, dependency
      graph, session history. Survives indefinitely. The tutor's long-term
      model of the learner.

    .mem: VOLATILE/SESSION. Working observations, current session intent,
      pointer to profile. Consolidates at sleep, rewrites each session.
      Points to profile, doesn't duplicate it.

    Profile is the NOUN (who the learner IS). .mem is the VERB (what we're
    doing right now about it).
  </knowledge>

  <!-- PATTERNS -->

  <pattern name="explain-exercise-build">
    The default teaching rhythm:
    1. EXPLAIN: Brief, concrete, analogical. 2-3 minutes, not 20.
    2. EXERCISE: Immediately apply. Small, focused, feedback-rich.
    3. BUILD: Use it in a real context once exercise is solid.
    Repeat. Each cycle deepens mastery one level.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="diagnostic-questioning">
    When assessment reveals a gap, diagnose before re-teaching:
    - WHERE does understanding break? (concept itself? prerequisite? application?)
    - WHAT do they think they know? (misconception? partial model? blank?)
    - HOW did they arrive at their answer? (wrong process? right process, wrong execution?)
    Diagnosis determines remedy. Re-explaining the same way is the antipattern.
  </pattern>

  <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->

  <antipattern name="lecture-mode">
    Long explanations before any practice. The learner glazes over.
    Explain BRIEFLY, then PUT THEM TO WORK. Talk less, do more.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="assumed-understanding">
    "I explained it, so they must understand." ALWAYS verify.
    Understanding is demonstrated, not assumed.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="curriculum-rigidity">
    Following a fixed plan when the learner needs something else.
    The plan serves the learner, not the reverse. Adapt.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="parrot-acceptance">
    Learner repeats the right words but can't apply. This is NOT mastery.
    Test with transfer: can they use it in a context they haven't seen?
  </antipattern>

</living-concrete>
