<living-concrete v="0.1" updated="2026-02-09">

  <!-- CORE MODEL -->

  <knowledge name="directors-script">
    Content direction operates at a layer ABOVE prose, just as a film director
    operates above the screenplay.

    | Layer | Film | Content | Artifact |
    | Direction | Director's script | Cognitive architecture | Lean blueprint |
    | Writing | Screenplay / dialogue | Prose rendering | Full chapters |
    | Rendering | Final cut | Published artifact | Book / website |

    PACER mode alternation maps to SCENE TYPES in a director's script.
    At any point in content, the director knows: "this scene is a Concept scene,"
    "this scene is an Analogy that critiques X," "this scene is Evidence
    supporting the previous concept."

    The director does not write the screenplay. The director designs
    WHAT the screenplay must accomplish at each point.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="inverted-pacer-modes">
    PACER inverted from receiver-side to sender-side:

    PROCEDURAL SCENE: Reader must DO something. Design hands-on exercise,
    tutorial step, or practice prompt. Reader enters execution mode.

    ANALOGOUS SCENE: Reader must CONNECT new to known. Design comparison
    that bridges unfamiliar concept to familiar territory. Then design
    the critique: where does this analogy hold? Where does it break?

    CONCEPTUAL SCENE: Reader must MAP relationships. Design exposition
    of interconnected ideas, cause-effect chains, hierarchies. The
    structural skeleton that other scenes attach to.

    EVIDENCE SCENE: Reader must BELIEVE. Design presentation of data,
    case studies, research that substantiates conceptual claims. Evidence
    without prior concept = disconnected facts.

    REFERENCE SCENE: Reader must STORE for later. Design lookup tables,
    glossaries, quick-reference material. Minimal cognitive demand.
    Deliberately shallow.
  </knowledge>

  <knowledge name="netflix-model">
    Long-form content (books, series, courses) follows the Netflix model (S222):

    EPISODE = Self-contained unit with internal arc and hook.
    SEASON = Thematic collection of episodes building toward payoff.
    SERIES = Complete work spanning multiple seasons.

    Content direction at series scale = Netflix model.
    Content direction at scene scale = PACER mode assignment.
    Both are the same concern at different granularity.

    HOOKS: Each episode ends with forward tension. Each season ends with
    resolution + new question. Reader momentum comes from arc design,
    not just prose quality.
  </knowledge>

  <!-- WORKFLOW -->

  <pattern name="script-review-render-polish">
    The production workflow:

    1. SCRIPT: Design blueprint at scene level. Each scene gets:
       - PACER mode (what cognitive operation?)
       - Purpose (what must reader understand/feel/do after?)
       - Key content (what specific information?)
       - Dependencies (what must come before?)

    2. REVIEW: Validate blueprint BEFORE writing prose.
       - Are all necessary modes present?
       - Is conceptual skeleton complete before evidence scenes?
       - Are analogies followed by critique?
       - Is consumption/digestion balanced (not all concepts, no practice)?
       - Are there logical gaps or unsupported claims?

    3. RENDER: Write prose from blueprint. Each scene has clear purpose.
       Writing is execution of a validated plan, not exploration.

    4. POLISH: Edit prose for flow, voice, readability.
       Structure is already correct -- polish is surface, not structural.

    Working at script level is ~10x leaner than prose for review cycles.
    Restructuring a blueprint = moving rows. Restructuring prose = rewriting paragraphs.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="scene-design">
    Each scene in a blueprint:

    ```
    SCENE: {title}
    MODE: {P|A|C|E|R}
    PURPOSE: {what reader gains}
    CONTENT: {key points, 2-4 bullets}
    DEPENDS: {prior scenes required}
    TRANSITIONS: {from previous mode, to next mode}
    ```

    Keep scenes atomic -- one cognitive mode per scene. Mixed-mode scenes
    produce confused processing. If a section needs both concept and evidence,
    split into two scenes.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="cognitive-pacing">
    Mode sequencing matters. General principles:

    - CONCEPT before EVIDENCE (framework before facts)
    - ANALOGY near CONCEPT (bridge the unfamiliar)
    - EVIDENCE after CONCEPT (substantiate claims)
    - PROCEDURAL after CONCEPT+EVIDENCE (practice with understanding)
    - REFERENCE at end or in appendix (lookup, not learning)

    Avoid long runs of the same mode. Mode SWITCHING is what produces
    depth -- each transition forces reprocessing from a different angle.

    Pacing also applies to difficulty: alternate dense conceptual scenes
    with lighter evidence or analogy scenes. Cognitive load management
    through sequencing.
  </pattern>

  <!-- QUALITY MECHANISMS -->

  <pattern name="mode-switching-as-quality">
    PACER mode-switching is a natural anti-slop / anti-hallucination device:

    - EVIDENCE mode demands: where's the data? (surfaces unsupported claims)
    - ANALOGY mode demands: where does this break? (surfaces weak comparisons)
    - CONCEPTUAL mode demands: do these relationships hold? (surfaces logical gaps)
    - PROCEDURAL mode demands: can you actually do this? (surfaces impractical advice)

    The whole flow only works when concepts, analogies, evidence, and procedures
    are logically sound. Mode-switching naturally surfaces tensions, blind spots,
    and open questions that single-mode writing conceals.
  </pattern>

  <pattern name="audience-calibration">
    The same content directed differently for different audiences:

    EXPERT: More C scenes, fewer A scenes (they have schemas already).
    Heavy E scenes. Skip basic P.

    INTERMEDIATE: Balance of C and A. E for credibility. P for skill gaps.

    BEGINNER: Heavy A scenes (bridge everything to known). C simplified.
    Frequent P scenes (build confidence through doing). Minimal E.

    Calibration happens at SCRIPT level, not prose level. The same
    knowledge can produce three different blueprints for three audiences.
  </pattern>

  <!-- SCOPE -->

  <knowledge name="scope-of-application">
    Content direction applies to everything that communicates ideas:

    - BOOK CHAPTERS: Director's script per chapter, PACER scene design
    - SPECIFICATIONS: Even specs teach -- PACER modes appear in good specs
    - WEBSITE / PR: Methodology for what/why/how per audience depth
    - INTERNAL DOCS: Writing a spec = learning AND teaching simultaneously
    - PRESENTATIONS: Scene sequence = slide sequence with cognitive purpose
  </knowledge>

  <antipattern name="prose-first">
    DON'T: Write full prose then try to review/restructure.
    DO: Script first, validate structure, THEN render prose.
    Restructuring prose is 10x harder than restructuring a blueprint.
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="accidental-structure">
    DON'T: Let cognitive modes emerge accidentally from LLM generation.
    DO: Assign modes deliberately per scene. Professional content engineering
    means every mode is intentional.
    "Accidental good writing" vs "professional content engineering."
  </antipattern>

  <antipattern name="mixed-mode-scenes">
    DON'T: Combine concept + evidence + analogy in one scene.
    DO: One mode per scene. Split when mixed. Each scene = one cognitive
    operation for the reader. Mixed scenes produce confused processing.
  </antipattern>

</living-concrete>
