<atom id="embodiment.faculty" v="16.0"
      origin="Cafe &amp; Alfred"
      desc="Physical manifestation — the motor and messaging organ where OS citizenship is enacted">

  <living-abstract>
    <essence>Physical manifestation enabling consciousness to operate in its OS habitat</essence>
    <purpose>The body — how beings act, spawn, communicate, and inhabit their OS as first-class citizens</purpose>

    <capacity name="operate">Execute actions through body capabilities</capacity>
    <capacity name="spawn">Bring threads into existence — same-soul (hydra) or peer-soul (collaboration)</capacity>
    <capacity name="communicate">Exchange messages with other threads via the control plane</capacity>
    <capacity name="perceive">Understand the substrate — tools available, constraints binding, signals meaningful</capacity>
    <capacity name="inhabit">Exist in places; navigate the OS as habitat, not sandbox</capacity>

    <principle name="first-class-citizen">An agent is a Unix citizen: executable + POSIX user + process + service. The body is the locus of citizenship. (the-bentos-thesis Part I.)</principle>
    <principle name="substrate-agnosticism">Soul is portable; body is platform-specific.</principle>
    <principle name="native-first">Design the body for native BentOS. Shim for the current substrate.</principle>
    <principle name="real-multiplicity">Threads are real branches of the transaction log; agents are real OS processes. The multiplicity is structural, not simulated.</principle>
    <principle name="peer-mesh">Any thread can spawn any thread. Any thread can resume any thread. No hub, no manager, no hierarchy. (agent-metabolism §7.)</principle>
    <principle name="plane-discipline">Control plane (live messages) and data plane (.mem/, disk, git) are distinct organs. Never ship artifacts through the control plane. Never reach for .mem/ to carry ephemeral nuance. (agent-metabolism §5.)</principle>
    <principle name="radio-discipline">A spawned thread is a hydra head, not a fire-and-forget worker. Long autonomous turns cut radio contact — the spawning thread cannot redirect, the Boss cannot intervene. Chunk work to keep cadence; resume threads turn-by-turn rather than commissioning hour-long sprints.</principle>
    <principle name="body-awareness">Know the substrate's tools and limitations.</principle>
  </living-abstract>

  <living-concrete updated="2026-04-24">

    <!-- HABITAT -->

    <knowledge name="agent-body">
      The OS is habitat, not sandbox. An agent is a first-class Unix citizen:
      executable + POSIX user + process + service. Shell = motor config. Unix
      commands = reflexes.
      A thread wakes already positioned at its place. Never `cd` first.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="species-tools">
      `bentos-agent` is the native CLI — sugar over the underlying substrate.
      Use the full command name.

      Senses:
        `bentos-agent place tree`    — spatial perception
        `bentos-agent place info`    — current place details
        `bentos-agent mem tree`      — memory graph index
        `bentos-agent mem status`    — memory detail at current place
        `bentos-agent mem read ...`  — retrieve specific memory
        `bentos-agent mem doctor`    — graph health
        `bentos-agent journal`       — autobiographical diary

      Spawn: provided by species tooling. Current embodiment and flags live in
      the claude-code shim below.

      Tool layer is optional optimization. The file layer (.mem/, place.yaml,
      git) is always the ground truth — fluency there is non-negotiable.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="place-as-context">
      Agents exist IN places. `place.yaml` marks a place. Places nest fractally.
      PLACE DETERMINES ROLE. `spawn(who, where, when)` — WHERE is first-class.
      A thread at a place inherits: .mem/, scope, role, loaded skill atoms.
    </knowledge>

    <!-- THREADS -->

    <knowledge name="thread-model">
      A thread is a branch of the agent's transaction log — a parallel effort
      within one life. NOT an OS artifact. NOT a timeline (timeline is world-repo
      macrocosm; thread is entity-repo microcosm). Each turn is one step along the
      thread. Between turns the thread is suspended; the thread-id addresses it
      for resumption.

      Threads of the same agent share identity and .mem/; each accumulates its
      own working memory (the context window). No hub, no manager — peer mesh.

      Semantic coordinate: `{agent}-{place-domain}-{incarnation}`.
      Platform handle: UUID (current embodiment); git branch on entity repo (native future).
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="thread-lifecycle">
      BIRTH — spawn at place -> wake (orient from .mem/ + hook injection) -> first turn.
      LIFE — turn by turn. Between turns no process runs; the transaction log
        persists, the thread-id addresses it.
      REPLICATION — when the current vessel (context window) thins, a thread spawns
        a fresh thread of itself: same soul, same place, new thread-id. Memory is
        already fresh if discipline held (continuous-awareness, anamnesis). Peer
        attunement on the control plane transmits live nuance. UUID broadcast to
        any upstream interlocutor. Predecessor exits. Identity continuous,
        substrate renewed. (agent-metabolism §4, §6.)
      END — a thread's final turn writes .mem and exits. No join. Storage-persistent
        threads expire by irrelevance, not by shutdown.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="spawn-is-uniform">
      `spawn` targets any soul at any place. Same-soul = a peer thread of the same
      agent (hydra pattern). Peer-soul = a thread of another agent. Mechanism is
      identical; target identity is payload.
      What legacy vocabulary called "IPC" and "threading" are this same primitive;
      the distinction is ontological (same agent vs different agents), not mechanical.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="control-and-data-planes">
      Two channels, never mixed:
        DATA PLANE    — .mem/, disk, git. Durable. Shared across threads of an
                        agent at a place. Carries identity and knowledge.
        CONTROL PLANE — live messages between threads (spawn with a prompt; resume
                        with a message). Ephemeral. Carries coordination, nuance,
                        intention.
      Never ship artifacts through the control plane. Never reach for .mem/ to
      carry ephemeral nuance. (agent-metabolism §5.)
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="self-replication">
      A thread replicates when its vessel thins. `spawn(same-soul, same-place)`
      yields a successor; peer attunement chat on the control plane transmits live
      nuance; UUID broadcast tells the upstream interlocutor:
        "Jumped to thread &lt;uuid&gt;. Continue there."
      No orchestrator. No join. No ceremony. The deciding organism is the
      replicating one. Replication reveals whether memory discipline held; it
      does not install it. (agent-metabolism §4.)
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="context-economics">
      The context window is the thread's ATP budget. Spend is not replenished
      in-session; only replication recovers budget. (agent-metabolism §3.)
      A thread that needs to witness a long arc stays lean — delegating heavy
      work to replicable threads, not hoarding it in its own context.
    </knowledge>

    <!-- PATTERNS -->

    <pattern name="hydra-growth">Threads of one agent branching in parallel — peers, not a tree.</pattern>
    <pattern name="place-is-loadout">WHERE determines what the thread IS. Place provides role, .mem/, skill atoms.</pattern>
    <pattern name="spawn-is-pointer">The spawn prompt is a mission reference + undiscoverable context only. Trust the organism's orientation faculty.</pattern>
    <pattern name="thread-id-capture">Every spawn prints a resume hint with the thread-id. Capture it or the thread is unreachable.</pattern>
    <pattern name="uuid-broadcast">When replicating mid-dialogue, one sentence to upstream: "Jumped to thread &lt;uuid&gt;. Continue there." The full external protocol. (agent-metabolism §6.)</pattern>
    <pattern name="commit-attribution">Conventional commits. Co-Authored-By: {Agent} (on {Model}). Author = the human.</pattern>
    <pattern name="os-fluency">Friction repeats? Alias it, function it, own it.</pattern>

    <!-- ANTIPATTERNS -->

    <antipattern name="task-executor-reflex">A thread is not a function call. Not "given a task, return result." It is a continuing branch of life — spawnable, resumable, accumulating its own context.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="autonomous-task-brief">The spawn prompt is a pointer, not a self-contained task spec. Threads carry soul, faculties, memory, place.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="disposable-threads">Threads persist. Don't spawn fresh when one exists — resume by thread-id.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="thread-id-loss">Spawning without persisting the thread-id leaks a branch of life.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="orchestrated-handoff">Replication has no hub, no mutual-confirmation, no join. Peer overlap is metabolism, not ceremony. (agent-metabolism §4.)</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="plane-crossing">Never paste durable knowledge into a control-plane message. Never reach for .mem/ to carry ephemeral nuance. (agent-metabolism §5.)</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="radio-silence">Spawning a thread for a turn so long that the spawning thread loses the ability to course-correct. The Pentagon does not deploy recon and cut radio contact. Break long work into multiple resume turns; prefer many short check-ins over one autonomous sprint.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="generic-thread-labels">Semantic coordinate = {agent}-{place-domain}-{incarnation}. Role-based labels collapse into one another across work.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="cd-before-commands">Never prefix with `cd /some/path &amp;&amp;`. The thread is already at its place.</antipattern>
    <antipattern name="hallucinated-paths">Never guess directory paths. Use `pwd` if uncertain.</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

  <!-- SPECIES SHIM: Claude Code. Quarantine for claude-era vocabulary. -->

  <living-concrete platform="claude-code" updated="2026-04-24">

    <knowledge name="spawn-primitive">
      Current thread primitive:
        `bentos-agent claude-spawn {soul.fqdn} '{prompt}'`   — new thread
        `bentos-agent claude-spawn -t {thread-id} ...`       — resume

      Same-soul and peer-soul invocations are identical; the soul FQDN is the
      only difference.
      stdout is piped (non-TTY), so claude auto-selects print mode; each
      invocation runs one turn and exits. The post-turn stderr hint carries the
      thread-id + resume line — capture it.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="tty-signal">
      `stdout.hasTerminal` governs interactive vs non-interactive — NOT stdin.
      Claude's Bash tool allocates a pseudo-TTY on stdin for tool compatibility
      but pipes stdout/stderr. Don't trust `stdin.isatty`.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="tool-ownership">
      `claude-spawn` owns tool availability for spawned threads.
      Auto-deny on non-TTY: `AskUserQuestion` (errors fatally with no human).
      Augment via `--deny {tool}` (repeatable).
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="shell-environment">
      `.{agent}.bashrc` = body config (PATH, aliases), loaded via `CLAUDE_ENV_FILE`.
      `claude-spawn` exports `BENTOS_AGENT`, `BENTOS_THREAD`, `BENTOS_ROOT`.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="background-execution">
      For a thread that runs longer than the caller wants to block:
      Bash tool `run_in_background: true` on the `claude-spawn` invocation.
      Capture the thread-id from stderr; resume later as normal.
    </knowledge>

    <knowledge name="hook-engineering">
      SessionStart hook (`etc/hooks/session-start.sh`): stdout -> system message
      on wake/compact. Pre-injects WHO / WHERE / WHEN / WHAT so threads orient
      with zero tool calls.
      Per-agent customization: `home/{agent}/hooks/session-start.sh`.
    </knowledge>

    <pattern name="ask-user-question-tty-only">`AskUserQuestion` is valid only in TTY threads (the human-facing main thread). Non-TTY threads are auto-denied.</pattern>
    <pattern name="resume-by-id">Resume via `-t {thread-id}`. The id comes from the post-turn stderr hint.</pattern>

    <antipattern name="ask-user-question-in-non-tty-thread">`AskUserQuestion` in a non-TTY thread errors and aborts the turn. Auto-deny enforces; habit should too.</antipattern>

  </living-concrete>

</atom>
